<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A narrative of the late Popish Plot in Ireland, for the subjugating thereof to the French king together with the proceedings against, and tryal of the Earl of Tyrone, and others who were accused for carrying on the same : containing the several examinations of Hubbart Bourke, Edward Ivie, John Macnemarrah, and Thomas Samson, Gent., upon information taken before the Lord Lieutenant and Council of Ireland ... / by Tho. Samson, Gent., late steward of the Earl of Tyrone.</title>
            <author>Samson, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S542</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202423</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36273212</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36273212</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150258</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93858)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150258)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2238:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A narrative of the late Popish Plot in Ireland, for the subjugating thereof to the French king together with the proceedings against, and tryal of the Earl of Tyrone, and others who were accused for carrying on the same : containing the several examinations of Hubbart Bourke, Edward Ivie, John Macnemarrah, and Thomas Samson, Gent., upon information taken before the Lord Lieutenant and Council of Ireland ... / by Tho. Samson, Gent., late steward of the Earl of Tyrone.</title>
                  <author>Samson, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sam. Lee and Dan. Major ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tyrone, Richard Power, --  Earl of, 1630-1690 --  Trials, litigation, etc.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:150258:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150258:2"/>
            <p>I do appoint <hi>Sam. Lee</hi> and <hi>Dan. Major</hi> of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> Stationers, to print this my Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, entituled, <hi>A Narrative of the late Popiſh Plot in</hi> Ireland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that no others print the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THO. SAMSON.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150258:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NARRATIVE OF THE Late Popiſh Plot IN IRELAND, For the Subjugating thereof to the FRENCH KING.</p>
            <p>Together with The Proceedings againſt, and Tryal of the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and others, who were accuſed for carrying on the ſame.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING</p>
            <list>
               <item>The ſeveral Examinations of <hi>Hubbart Bourke, Edward Ivie, John Macnemarrah,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Samſon,</hi> Gent. upon Information taken before the Lord Lieutenant and Council of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The large promiſes of Rewards and Favours made to the Perſons aforeſaid, in caſe they would have been induced to deſiſt from proſecuting the ſaid Earl, and to affirm that they had been ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borned by others to accuſe him.</item>
               <item>The many Threats made to all, and Puniſhments inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one of the ſaid Witneſſes after they had peremptorily declared their reſolution to diſcover what they knew concerning the ſaid Plot.</item>
               <item>The manner of the Proceedings againſt the ſaid Earl at <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>-Aſſizes, 1679. with the Names of the Jury, and the Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the King's Evidence met with before, at, and ſince the ſaid Aſſizes.</item>
            </list>
            <p>By <hi>Tho. Samſon</hi> Gent. late Steward to the Earl of <hi>Tyrone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Lee,</hi> and <hi>Dan. Major;</hi> at the Feathers in <hi>Lumbard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> and Hand and Scepter in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150258:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150258:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable ARTHUR EARL of <hi>ESSEX.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT may be thought that the frequent method of Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to Perſons of Honour, now ſo much uſed, might be the occaſion of this my Addreſs to your Lordſhip; but I humbly conceive it moſt abſolutely neceſſary for my Preſervation, to flie to your Lordſhip for Protection and Relief: for the very Name of <hi>King's Evidence</hi> is now (by the ſubtilty of evil and guilty men) grown ſo obnoxious to many, that no man who hath the courage to appear for his King and Country againſt the Papiſts, can receive other Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from many men, than that uſually given to Rogues, Barra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or common Diſturbers of the Peace of their Neighbours. But, my Lord, this Diſcovery now laid at your Lordſhips feet, is of a far different nature, and ſuch which every good Chriſtian and Subject is bound in Conſcience to make for the good of his King and Country; and being no other than what hath been before the Lord Lieutenant and Council of that Kingdom in which your Honour did formerly reſide as Chief Ruler under his Majeſty, I therefore have made bold to dedicate theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to your Honour; you being acquainted with the Intereſts and Humours of that People, can beſt judge what Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſuch as appear for Proteſtancy and the Engliſh Intereſt lie under in that Kingdom: All perſons favouring us there, are maliciouſly termed our Promoters. I do therefore humbly pray your Lordſhip to accept of this my poor Endeavour; which done, I ſhall not doubt its acceptance from all good men, and ſhall remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Honour's moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant, <hi>THO. SAMSON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:150258:4"/>
            <head>An Introductory TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Northern part of the World lying ſo much in the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Roman Church, that its converſion to the Popiſh Reli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on is the Mark that many venture their Allegiance, Life, and Eſtate at, having nought elſe but to be Canonized for their good work if they miſs their aim therein; and I hope good Proteſtants cannot believe that Sect of men will lay down the Cudgels if their Jeſuitical Deſignes prevail not, but will venture on the old way of Blouding, if need require.</p>
            <p>Hence it is that their Plotting is not confined to <hi>England</hi> onely, but it must croſs the Seas into <hi>Ireland</hi> alſo, though they land in the boſoms of pretended Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>And it cannot be imagined, but that the Deſigne was carried on at one and the ſame time both on this and that ſide of the Water, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods uſed for the carrying on of their Deſignes the ſame; as by former Nary at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> compared with the following Informations and Examinations, will appear, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By raiſing of Forces, by pretended ſettlements of Eſtates, to prevent its forfeiture in caſe of diſcovery, or uſing the old drudging way of aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Evidence; and if all theſe fail, promiſing Bribes for rewards on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thereby to ſhair the Truth.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it pleaſed God to diſappoint their Endeavours in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by ſome who were intruſted by them, whom God plucked from them to pull us as Brands out of the fire; ſo here, what knowledge was obtained, came from ſome who were to be Actors in the ſame Tragedy; ſo that the Wiſh might be taken in their own Craft, and the Hand of God might be ſeen in the preſervation of our King, Country, and Religion: Such our Deliverers having changed their Bulls, Pardons, and Abſolutions of the Pope, and a horrid bloudy Act to be committed, for fear of God, peace of Conſcience, loyalty to their King, and praiſe of good men.</p>
            <p>And as in the Ganponden-Treaſon a Letter from one privie thereto did diſcover the ſame; ſo likewiſe in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> in <hi>1641,</hi> it was a Letter from one Iriſhman to another which made the Engliſh to ſecure the City and Caſtle of <hi>Dublin;</hi> which otherwiſe might have followed the fate of the whole Nation, or greateſt part of that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And why might not perſons as much queſtion the truth of that being ſo diſcovered and prevented, as the truth of all thoſe Plottings now in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion? and the rather, it being now a Crime in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to call thoſe late murthering bloudy times Rebellion, but a now name is taken up for it, namely, <hi>A Civil War.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150258:4"/>
            <p>In this preſent Diſcovery it was alſo a Letter that gave notice of the things declared to be deſigned; which concurring with other teſtimony, did convince one of the Witneſſes of the reality of their Deſignes.</p>
            <p>And indeed it's not to be queſtioned, but moſt of the good Proteſtants of that Kingdom, I mean ſuch as are not got into Preferments, or married in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Papiſt Families, and thereby become any thing as to Religion, (ſuch I ſay) are fully ſatisfied of their Plottings, and the rather, conſidering the info<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the Papiſts, and the many of them, the power the Prieſts and Romiſh Clergie have over them. And were it not for fear of firing their houſes, and maſſacring their. perſon and families, and the ſcandal of diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (though the truth) (and the greateſt bindrance of all is) knowing that their Tryals, if impeached, nuſt be by ſome of their own Faction, and it may be as much concerned is themſelves; and ſo conſequently would be cleared. Many Papiſts in <hi>Ireland</hi> valuing more to ſwear by a piece of Iron, Wood, or Stone, a pretended Relick of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, Chappel, or Bell, than on the holy Bible which I have my ſelf known, that after they have for ſworn themſelves on the Bible, have confeſſed, to their damage, the truth, when ſworn on that Relick.</p>
            <p>But I do not queſtion but that God may open the eyes of ſome of the beſt of that Nation, as to appear for the Truth,
<note place="margin">And when Mr. <hi>David Fitz-Gerrald</hi>'s Information be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes viſible.</note> and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Reputation of thoſe that have already ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and ſtop the mouths of Gainſayens.</p>
            <p>Let others make it their buſineſs ſo much as they can, to aſperſe all that appear as Evidence for their King, and thereby make informing odious by Ballads and Pomphlets; I am ſure ſo long as there is no Law againſt Allegiance, but onery the Prieſts pardon for it, ſome mens Conſciences will once be a wakened, and then men will not fear to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; and Papiſts Oaths will be leſs val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed againſt Proteſtants, or at leaſt, as little valued as they value the Bible they ſwear by: For it's well known by woful experience to ſome, what a many of falſe Oaths have been taken by Papiſts againſt Proteſtants,
<note place="margin">As the preſent Lord Mayor of <hi>London</hi> and his Agents have ſufficiently ſuffered in.</note> to the great prejudice of their Eſtates. Which when, I ſay, all ſuch conſiderations of fear are lain aſide, then you will have greater Torches enlightned by our ſmall Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to make all things plain unto you. And though now things ſeem to be in a ſwoon, Plots being turned into Intrigues, time will come when Plots will be called Plots; Popery, Popery; Rebellion, not Civil War, but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion.</p>
            <p>Having made this ſhort Preface, I ſhall refer the Reader to the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations and Examinations themſelves, to enquire into matter of fact, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring them to judge us according to the merit of the Cauſe, and not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding unto the Papiſts Scandals.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="names">
            <pb facs="tcp:150258:5"/>
            <head>The Perſons Names that were indicted for High-Treaſon at <hi>Waterford</hi>-Aſſizes, the 11th of <hi>March,</hi> 1679.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Bradly</hi> Eſq;</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Names of the Perſons accuſed in the Conſpiracy.</head>
               <item>Gountie of <hi>Waterford, James Power,</hi> the Father.</item>
               <item>Gountie of <hi>Waterford, Richard Power</hi> the Sons.</item>
               <item>Gountie of <hi>Waterford, William Power</hi> the Sons.</item>
               <item>Gountie of <hi>Waterford, James Power</hi> the Sons.</item>
               <item>Gountie of <hi>Waterford,</hi> Dr. <hi>Moore.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gountie of <hi>Waterford, William Fince.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gountie of <hi>Waterford, Lawrance Swillivaitt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gountie of <hi>Waterford,</hi> Quarter-Maſter <hi>Ely.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gountie of <hi>Waterford, Paul Strong.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gountie of <hi>Waterford, Richard Power.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gountie of <hi>Waterford, John Power,</hi> that killed the Lord <hi>Mohun,</hi> as is ſaid.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Turlo Macmahan.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>County of <hi>Limbrick,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>County of <hi>Limbrick,</hi> Col. <hi>Peirce Lacy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>County of <hi>Limbrick,</hi> Lord <hi>Brittas.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>County of <hi>Limbrick,</hi> Sir <hi>John Fitz-Gerrald.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>County of <hi>Limbrick, David Fitz-Gerrald,</hi> who hath ſince con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed himſelf to be concerned with the reſt.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Counſel appearing for the ſaid Earl.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>Counſellor <hi>Porter,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Counſellor <hi>Longon,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>and</item>
                  <item>Three Atturney &amp; Sollicitors.</item>
               </list> which were all allowed.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150258:5"/>
            <head>The INFORMATION of Hubart Bourke Gent. Exhibited to the Lord Lieutenant and Council of <hi>IRELAND</hi> as followeth.</head>
            <opener>Who ſaith,</opener>
            <p>THat on or about the laſt day of <hi>October</hi> 1678, I was at <hi>Kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mac Thomas</hi> in the County of <hi>Waterford,</hi> in the company of one <hi>Richard Power</hi> Gent. and <hi>Thomas Samſon</hi> Gent. Seneſchal and Steward to the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> where after Breakfaſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The ſaid <hi>Samſon</hi> told me, That the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> deſired him to pray me to come to him that night or the day following; and that his Lordſhip had ſome Concerns to confer with me about, which he the ſaid <hi>Samſon</hi> knew not what they were (as he told me.) I accordingly went the ſame night to the Earl his houſe at <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roghmore</hi> with the ſaid <hi>Samſon,</hi> who went into the Parlor to the ſaid Earl, and acquainted him therewith; and the ſaid <hi>Samſon</hi> reurning to me, told me that his Lordſhip was at Supper with Strangers, and could not ſpeak with me that night; but deſired me to come the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: which I accordingly did. After wellcome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His Lordſhip ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me what News? I told his Lordſhip, I preſumed that he had the beſt correſpondency in that part of the Countrey, and that for my part I had none worth his Lordſhips hearing. I have (ſaith he) received Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence out of <hi>France,</hi> where I underſtand that the French are very powerful; and that <hi>Parlez vouz Francoize</hi> will be plentifully heard here ere long. I asked his Lordſhip what great Exploits the French King had done? Done (ſaid he) Hath done Wonders, and we may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, call him <hi>Defendor of the Faith:</hi> He beſt deſerves it, and I am ſure the hand of God is with him. My Lord, ſaid I, a man would be apter to think, that if the French were intended that way, he would rather venture on <hi>England</hi> firſt, than come hither.</p>
            <p>I have received a Letter, ſaith he, from one <hi>Robert Power,</hi> who ſtudies the Law at one of the Courts at <hi>London,</hi> That the French have a great ſtroke in <hi>England</hi> already; and (ſays he) before you are half a year older the French will ſubdue both <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ineland,</hi> and little harm thereby; for they in <hi>England</hi> have no Faith in them: For they no ſooner grant a thing, than recall it again, juſt as they have dealt with me about the Lands of <hi>Deaces:</hi> but, ſaid he, before they enjoy it, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog</hi> I will loſe the beſt blood in my Body. Then my Lord, ſaid I, if the French come hither, they will kill all us poor Subjects. As for that, ſaith he, I have made my Conditions for this ſide of the Countrey; and if you will joyn with me, I will put you in a ready way to get an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. I told his Lordſhip that I wanted it much, but could not tell how to come at it. With that his Lordſhip drew out of his Pocket a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150258:6"/>great quantity of Papers roled up, and deſired me to ſign unto it; where upon a ſudden glance I could read the Names of <hi>Paul Strong, Richard</hi> and <hi>John Power;</hi> and do believe there were the Names of One hundred Subſcribers. I deſired his Lordſhip to excuſe me for the preſent, and that I was unfit to be employed in ſuch matters: And moreover, that I never heard of any of my name that proved Traitors to their King, and I would not begin. With that his Lordſhip called me Coward, and drew his Sword almoſt out of his Scabbard to kill me; but he eſpied a Gentleman coming, which was Sir <hi>John Ponſoby</hi>'s Son. Then my Lord went to greet him, and after he had uſhered him into his houſe, his Lordſhip goes himſelf unto the Bridge at <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roghmore,</hi> and called to <hi>William Power</hi> a Brogmaker, and deſired him in all haſte to call <hi>John Daniel</hi> unto him, to inform againſt me; for that I had beaten the ſaid <hi>Daniel</hi> in my own defence half a year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for which the ſaid <hi>Daniel</hi> forgave me, before four Witneſſes; yet the ſaid <hi>Daviel</hi> was forced to inform againſt me. And the Earl threatned that if he did not, he ſhould loſe his Ears: On which I was diſarmed, and by a <hi>Mittimus</hi> ſent to <hi>VVaterford</hi> Gaol. And it being Saturday late at night, the Conſtable took my word to meet him at a certain place the Monday morning following. In the mean time I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured Bail, and brought them to <hi>Curroghmore;</hi> which Bail the Lord of <hi>Tyrone</hi> refuſed: and his Lordſhip alſo ſent to ſeveral Juſtices of the Peace, that they ſhould not bail me on any account: And his Lordſhip ſaid further, That if I did not ſtarve in Priſon, he would hang me the next Aſſizes. Then going towards <hi>Waterford</hi> Gaol, I wrote a Letter to <hi>VVilliam Smith</hi> Eſquire, that he would ſpeak to my Lord in my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, to take Bail for me; who promiſed he would: but his Lordſhip refuſed to do the ſame, when again Bail was tendred. And then I was ſent to <hi>VVaterford</hi> Gaol the beginning of <hi>November,</hi> and there remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed until the 14th of <hi>March</hi> following, although there were five Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters written to his Grace the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> by me complaining to his Grace of the Miſuſage I had received, and containing what farther I had to ſay. Which Letters either miſcarried, or were taken up at the Poſt Office at <hi>VVaterford,</hi> that the Lord Lieutenant never recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them, nor no account given to his Grace of them; as his Grace was pleaſed to ſay.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <head>The Further EXAMINATION of Hubart Bourke.</head>
            <p>WHo further ſaith, That after I was ſent for by his Grace the Lord Lieutenant and Council in <hi>March</hi> following, and was ordered to attend the Court of the Kings Bench, and the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> to anſwer, I accordingly appeared there, and was charged by the Earls People, his Attourney Mr. <hi>Buckner,</hi> his Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Thomas Cowdall,</hi> and one <hi>Mac Carty</hi> Deputy Clerk of the Crown for <hi>Munſter</hi> Circuit; where the fore-mentioned perſons brought an Indictment againſt me for Stealing of Horſe out of the County of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150258:6"/>
               <hi>Cleare,</hi> which, as they pretended, was about three years before. Which was but a Contrivance (as it was found upon Trial) by the Judges of the Kings Bench, thereby to render me infamous; that my Evidence againſt the ſaid Earl might be of no value: where I was bound to proſecute the ſaid <hi>Earl</hi> at <hi>Waterford</hi> Aſſizes next enſuing.</p>
            <p>Note, That this <hi>Cowdall</hi> was the foreſaid <hi>Powers</hi> man, and <hi>Mac Carty</hi> one who was under promiſes to diſcover all ſecrets to the Earl, that he knew as Clerk of the Crown.</p>
            <p>But being bound to proſecute the ſaid Earl at <hi>Waterford,</hi> I was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged from appearing there, ſeveral people telling me that I ſhould never return from thence; in regard the ſaid Earl had procured one of his own Council to be Judge of that Aſſizes, and his own Tenants and Relations to be Tryers of the Matter, and that at his own Door and Countrey. All which ſo affrighted me, that I choſe rather to hazard my Recognizance and forfeiture of my Bonds, than to endanger my Life; which I underſtood was ſought for.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding all Threats, I went to <hi>Waterford</hi> Aſſizes, but finding the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> and his Cozen, Lieuten. <hi>Thomas Power,</hi> lodging and dietting in the ſame houſe with the Judges; and being told in <hi>Waterford,</hi> that if I opened my lips againſt the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone;</hi> that I ſhould not ſleep that Night following, unleſs I ſlept to Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Which Threat daunted me much, alſo wanting <hi>John Mac Namara</hi> his Aſſiſtance of his Teſtimony, which by promiſe of Reward by the ſaid Earl, he was kept from affording me.</p>
            <p>And not having then forced Mr. <hi>Thomas Samſon</hi> to bring in his Teſtimony, nor Mr. <hi>Edward Ivie</hi> his; all which I knew could diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver much in this matter, was the Cauſe why I left the Court and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented my ſelf, thinking it would be better at the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> by which time thoſe Perſons before-mentioned would be brought in.</p>
            <p>Further, In order thereunto, I wrote a Letter to the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Keeting,</hi> and Sr. <hi>Richard Reynolls,</hi> the Judges then at <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> That I was not then prepared to proceed, the Witneſſes being not brought in, with ſuch like Excuſes; but fearing the Letter ſhould not be delivered, and not daring to go to the Judges Chamber, by reaſon of the Earls being there, and his Friends and Servants, I went into the Court; where as ſoon as I appeared, the Lord Chief Juſtice called, as I thought unto the Gaoler, to take me into Cuſtody; which affrightened me ſo, that I went away out of the Court, and ſuch a Hue and Cry was made after me, by the Gaoler, Conſtables, and Bailliffs, that I was glad to go into one Mr. <hi>Fullars</hi> Tann-houſe near <hi>Waterſord,</hi> and there to ſtay all that night. In the mean time the Gaoler goes where my Horſe was, and told the people he was ordered by the Judges to ſecure my Horſe. The next morning by break of day I hired a Boat, to ferry me over to the Slip houſe in <hi>Killkenny</hi> ſide and County, and went into one Mr. <hi>William VVilkenſon</hi>'s houſe, an Inn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper, who about four of the Clock in the afternoon told me that it was not ſafe for me to ſtay in his houſe, in regard there was ſo great a ſearch and inquiry made after me in <hi>VViterford.</hi> Whereupon I took Mr. <hi>VVilkenſon</hi>'s advice, and went two miles on foot towards <hi>Killken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;</hi> intending to go to his Grace the Lord Lioutenant, who was then there, and to acquaint his Grace with the proceedings; but Major <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards</hi> his Coachman, one who lived with the ſaid Earl not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, overtook me in the way, and rid before me to an Alehouſe,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150258:7"/>where he writ a Letter to the Earls Coachman <hi>William Finch,</hi> that he the ſaid <hi>Finch</hi> ſhould acquaint his Lord of my going towards <hi>Killkenny;</hi> which Letter I accidentally diſcovered: which cauſed me to leave the Road, and to go to a place called the <hi>Gurteenes,</hi> and there to ſtay four or five days, until <hi>John Mac Namara,</hi> who had diſcourſed the Matter with the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> ſent a Letter unto me, in which he ſaid that the ſaid Earl ſwore and dam'd himſelf to Eternity that he owed me no ill will at all, praying me to come to his Houſe; but being ſo afraid of my ſafety, I told him that I could not.</p>
            <p>I then writ a Letter in few days after unto the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> for my Linnen and other things that were at his houſe, who returned the Meſſenger to me with a Letter without my Linnen; wherein he menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned that he would meet me the next morning at <hi>Waterford,</hi> and have my things there with him, and that he had ſeveral things to impart unto me concerning the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> which he durſt not write: ſo meeting accordingly the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara,</hi> his Wife and Father-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law <hi>Teege Finiean</hi> at Mrs. <hi>Jarvies</hi> her houſe, I told him that I was ready to go on Ship-board for <hi>England.</hi> Never trouble your ſelf farther, faid <hi>Mac Namara,</hi> for I will get you a good Conſideration and Liberty to ſtay in <hi>Ireland;</hi> the aforeſaid <hi>Finican</hi> alſo promiſed me 20 <hi>s.</hi> and one Barrel of Beer he had at home, and he would lend me his Horſe to ride to his houſe to drink part thereof; the ſaid <hi>M. Namara</hi> telling me that I was not in caſe at preſent to take ſuch a Journey (meaning to <hi>England</hi>) and ſo they flattered me home with them: Which I ſtill underſtood by their Diſcourſe, that it was on the Earls accompt that they invited me.</p>
            <p>Two days after my coming to <hi>M. Namara</hi> his Houſe, he went and informed the ſaid Earl therewith, and told me, coming home from the Earl of <hi>Tyrones,</hi> that the ſaid Earl preſented his Service unto me, and deſired me to give Major <hi>Butler</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Rouan</hi> a meeting at a certain place, in order to agree with me; which thing I imparted to Mr. <hi>Edward Ivie,</hi> he living in the ſame Town where the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> dwelled. Mr. <hi>Ivie</hi> deſired me to be wary, for fear they ſhould intrap me; on which I told Mr. <hi>Ivie</hi> I would go and ſee what they would be at: In order to which reſolution, Mr. <hi>Mac Namara</hi> and my ſelf, met them the ſaid Major <hi>Butler</hi> and <hi>Rouan,</hi> about four Miles from the ſaid <hi>Mac Numara</hi> his houſe, where Ale was ſold; and reaſoning the matter together, the ſaid Major <hi>Butler</hi> deſired me to deſiſt troubling the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> any further, and the ſaid Earl would give me a good Farm and Stock, and the ſaid Earls Favour for evermore, than ever his Lordſhip ſhewed to any before; and willed me to name any Sum of Money that I pleaſed, and he the ſaid <hi>Butler,</hi> would be bound for the payment hereof, on Condition that I the ſaid <hi>Bourke,</hi> would not any more trouble the ſaid Earl; but that I would ſay, that Eſq; <hi>Villiars,</hi> Capt. <hi>Nicholls,</hi> Mr. <hi>May,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bradly,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Peter Anthony,</hi> were my Aſſiſtants and Promoters in this Diſcovery and Deſign againſt the ſaid Earl.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwered, That neither of the Parties mentioned, ever ſpake a word to me concerning ſuch things in all their lives, and if they had, I would not be prompted to ſuch an unjuſt Action by any of them; and that I never charged the ſaid Earl with any thing, but what the ſaid Earl was pleaſed to tell and ſhew unto me himſelf.</p>
            <p>After they had kept me there until it was almoſt night, then Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor <hi>Butler</hi> ſent <hi>Rouan</hi> home unto the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and Major <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150258:7"/>came himſelf with me, and <hi>Mc. Namara,</hi> home to <hi>Mc. Namara</hi> his houſe; where the ſaid Major and my ſelf lay that night together: all which Diſcourſe of our meeting afore-mentioned, I acquainted Mr. <hi>Ivie</hi> with. Then I reſolved to go into <hi>England,</hi> but Mr. <hi>Ivie</hi> told me that it that it was not ſafe to go, before I had the Lord Lieutenant his Paſs. Now upon that ſaying I knew not what to do, for want of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency to apply my ſelf unto the Lord Lieutenant; and alſo being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to go alone, I then went to <hi>Waterford,</hi> where I met one of the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi>'s Servants, named <hi>John Whelen,</hi> who told me before Mrs. <hi>Jarvis</hi> and her Servants, that it ſtood me inſtead to run away at the Aſſizes, for if I had ſtayed, the Judges were reſolved at leaſt to crop my Ears; and Mr. <hi>Wilkenſon</hi> afore-named, told me that the Judges were reſolved to take me along the Circuit with them, and to indict me at <hi>Ennis,</hi> and hang me if they could.</p>
            <p>I alſo writ a Letter to the Earl of <hi>Orrery,</hi> which the aforeſaid <hi>Edward Ivie</hi> was to carry to the ſaid Earl, the ſaid <hi>Ivie</hi> having occaſion of his own into thoſe parts. (Which Letter the ſaid <hi>Ivie</hi> read before it was ſealed.) The contents of the ſaid Letter was to pray the Earl of <hi>Orre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to ſend for and examine the aforeſaid Mr. <hi>Samſon,</hi> who was then at <hi>Youghall</hi> (near the ſaid Earl) and to write to his Grace the Lord Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, deſiring him to ſend for the ſaid Mr. <hi>Samſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ivie,</hi> and my ſelf; but Mr. <hi>Ivie</hi> being buſie in ordering his Harveſt, could not go ſo ſoon, as he intended, to the Earl of <hi>Orrery</hi>'s: In the mean time, when the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> could not by Bribes or otherwiſe, prevail with me to deſiſt, he then petitioned the Lord Lieutenant againſt me, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon a Purſivant was ſent to the Earl of <hi>Tyrones</hi> firſt, and told him that he was ordered to take his Directions for the ſecuring of me; and being taken, I ſhould be brought before the ſaid Earl firſt: And the ſaid Earl, to cloak his knowledge where I lay (as if he was ignorant of the ſame) ſent ſeveral of his Servants to ſearch after me; who all knew where I was, having often ſent unto me before; who coming into the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> his houſe about Ten or Eleven of the Clock at night, the ſaid Earls Servants apprehended me and bound me with Ropes; but when I ſaw the Purſivant, I asked him, Whether he had a Warrant? Who told me that he was but a Spectator, and they (meaning the Earls Servants) were the Officers; and withal he bad me take leave and laſt farewel of my Friends.</p>
            <p>Then they brought me away from Mr. <hi>Mac Namara</hi> his houſe four miles that night, and next morning they carried me tied with Ropes (out of the way we were to go) to <hi>Waterford,</hi> until they came to the Croſs there; and then they went into Mr. <hi>Guddridge</hi> his houſe, an Inn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper, and there ſtayed me until all the Earls Friends in the Town, and all the Officers in the Town came to ſee me in that Caſe. And then they procured a lame unſhod little Garren for me to ride on, and tied my Legs under the Horſes or Garrens Belly, and ſo carried me out of the way, thorow the Town to the other end thereof; having many Spectators: and then carried me back to the ſaid Earls Houſe at <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roghmore</hi> (ſo bound) where the Earl had many Friends gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſee me come in that manner; and ſo left me to the Earls plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>After they had ſtayed me at the ſaid Earls, after the manner afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, about two hours, then they carried me on the way to <hi>Carigme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;</hi> and <hi>Thomas Power,</hi> the Earls chief Gentleman, rid before us to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150258:8"/>
               <hi>Crehanah,</hi> to Major <hi>Butlers</hi> Houſe, to deſire him to meet me in the way, which accordingly he did; and asked me, as if he had not known what was the matter? I anſwered him that I did not know. Said the Major to me, Can I ſpeak with you in private? I told him that there was no fit place for him to ſtay, for I was wet and dirty with riding ſo far in dirty ways without Boots with my Leggs tied. Then the ſaid <hi>Butler</hi> followed me to <hi>Carigmeſure,</hi> and brought with him <hi>John Rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> aforeſaid and Quarter-maſter <hi>Ely;</hi>
               <note place="margin">No queſtion but he knew the reſt, being all Papiſts.</note> the ſaid <hi>Ely</hi> ſaying, That he knew the reſt of the Company, but me he knew not. I anſwered him that he knew me too, if he would acknowledg it, but I was indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent whether he would or not. I know you ſo well, ſaid <hi>Ely,</hi> that one rope is too little for you. Then Major <hi>Butler</hi> and <hi>Rouan</hi> fell again to the old way of corrupting me by turns, and the Major promiſed me that if I would do as he before deſired, that he would follow me next Morning to <hi>Killkenny,</hi> and get me rid of any further trouble; if I would take their former proffers, and accuſe the fore-named Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: and that there were a People before me at <hi>Killkenny,</hi> that would be very glad that theſe Gentlemen aforeſaid, ſhould be brought in to the ſaving of the Earl of <hi>Tyrone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I refuſed and ſcorned their offers, notwithſtanding the great ſhame and pain they put me to. Major <hi>Butler</hi> then took me by the hand, and ſaid Old Friend farewel now for evermore. Then Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-maſter <hi>Ely</hi> began a Health, to the Proſperity of the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and to the confounding and utter Subverſion of all his Enemies; and forced the Health to go round.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Ely</hi> is the Lord Lieutenant his Quarter-maſter, and charged by the aforeſaid <hi>Mac Namara,</hi> in his after Examination, of being in the Plot, and to be a Major under the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> for the French King, and confeſſed that he was a Papiſt heretofore, when queſtioned by the Lord Lieutenant upon the aforeſaid Mr. <hi>Samſon</hi>'s telling him before the Lord Lieutenant and Council, that he had a Crucifix about his Neck, and afterwards was committed to the Marſhal for abuſing the ſaid <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> where he continued for one week, and then returned to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
            <p>The Examination which follows is Mr. <hi>Ivie</hi>'s, touching the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge he had of Mr. <hi>Mac Namara,</hi> which was before ſpoken of to be concerned with the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> in the Plot; and who afterwards in his Examination confeſſeth he was to be an Officer under the ſaid Earl: who promiſed me before the ſaid Mr <hi>Ivie,</hi> to diſcover the ſame at the Aſſizes; but through Bribes did not appear: but managed the Earls Deſigns with me, to bribe me to deſiſt my proſecuting the ſaid Earl; and offered me large Bribes to throw the Accuſation on others. But on Mr. <hi>Ivies</hi> confronting him before the Lord Lieutenant and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, and petitioning the Board to have him kept from the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi>'s Friends and Agents, and from Quarter-maſter <hi>Ely,</hi> who fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed him with Money and Horſe, and promiſed him Bail on occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: He then being kept cloſe, according to the ſaid <hi>Ivie</hi>'s Petition, he then confeſſed the Truth, and diſcovered the whole Plot; as you may ſee in his Examination following Mr. <hi>Ivie</hi>'s.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BART BO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150258:8"/>
            <head>The EXAMINATION of Edward Ivie Gent. Taken at ſeveral Times before the Lord Lieutenant and Council of <hi>IRELAND,</hi> in the beginning of <hi>November</hi> 1679, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Earl of <hi>TYRONE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHo ſaith, That about <hi>Michaelmaſs</hi> laſt was Twelve-month, <hi>John Mac Namara</hi> of the County of <hi>Waterford</hi> Gentleman, brought unto me <hi>James Power</hi> the Father, and his three Sons, <hi>Richard, William,</hi> and <hi>James Power;</hi> the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> deſiring me to take them as Tenants on the Lands of <hi>Dunhill,</hi> in the ſaid County of <hi>Waterford;</hi> which accordingly I did, the ſaid <hi>Mac Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mara</hi> aſſuring me that they were honeſt men: who after that they had been there ſome time, I obſerved together with my Servants and Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, a great recourſe to them of perſons, being private in the ſaid <hi>Power</hi>'s houſe by day, and going away at night; having ſeveral ſtrange horſes at day, and gone away at night. I alſo obſerved the ſaid <hi>Powers</hi> and the aforeſaid <hi>John Mac Namara</hi> providing Bridles, Saddles, Swords, and other Arms.</p>
            <p>In the mean time a Warrant was ſent from his Grace the Lord Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, to apprehend the ſaid <hi>Powers</hi> and <hi>Mac Namara:</hi> The <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> being apprehended, made their Eſcape out of the Conſtables hands; which the Countrey took much notice of: <hi>Mac Namara</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo taken, was committed to <hi>Waterford</hi> Gaol, and in few days bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out; on which he returned home, and ſome days after told me, that he had made his application to the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> to aſſiſt him in this his trouble: And finding the ſaid Earl in fear, on <hi>Bourke</hi>'s charging him for Treaſon, ſo that he did not anſwer the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi>'s ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation; he the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> returned home in great paſſion, and concluded that his Father-in-law and Brother-in-law ſhould go to <hi>Dublin</hi> to get his Pardon; which accordingly they did, and applied themſelves to Sir <hi>John Cole</hi> for their Aſſiſtance: And as they told me, they met at Sir <hi>John Cole</hi>'s the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Keeting,</hi> on which they concluded to get no Pardon; for that the Lord Chief Juſtice had promiſed to be kind to the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara,</hi> and would ſtand his Friend at the Aſſizes. Upon which they returned home, and acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> with what they had done. But the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> concluded himſelf not ſafe, in their not bringing his Pardon, and therefore broke out into a great paſſion, and told me that ſeeing the ſaid Earl had drawn him into ſuch dangerous Deſigns, and had now left him, he would no more look after Pardons, nor truſt no more to promiſes, but he would diſcover the whole Truth, which the Earl
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150258:9"/>of <hi>Tyrone</hi> was carrying on againſt the King; and further ſaid, That <hi>Bourke</hi> was but a Fool, and knew nothing of the Plot, in compariſon of what he knew; and that at the Aſſizes he would make a full Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thereof.</p>
            <p>The ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> further told me, that the ſaid Earl was pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy to all the Horſes and Arms provided for the Plot, which when the ſaid <hi>Bourke</hi> came into the Countrey, I acquainted him with; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the ſaid <hi>Bourke</hi> wrote a Letter to the Judges, wherein he menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, that the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> and others were concerned in the Plot, and therefore he could not appear till they appeared: The ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> hiding himſelf, until he had received an Account of Mr. <hi>Bourk</hi>'s Proceedings and of the return of the Letter ſent to the Judges, in order to his coming in to diſcover; that he might be ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. To which purpoſe the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> received a Letter from a Friend of his, That <hi>Bourke</hi> had not yet ſpoke with the Judges, and therefore adviſed the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> to continue private where he was, until he heard further from him. At this time <hi>Mac Namara</hi> had promiſed <hi>Bourke</hi> to confeſs, but deſiſted on the Earls Promiſes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> hearing of the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara's</hi> Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſeveral Letters was poſted after the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara,</hi> in order to get him to <hi>Waterford;</hi> with promiſes of being prorected from all things which was lain to his Charge. Upon which promiſes the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> came to <hi>Waterford,</hi> and there was privately ſecured in the houſe of Mr. <hi>Fitz Gerrald</hi> a Papiſt and Merchant, and the ſame night, or the night after, was conveyed up to the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi>'s Lodgings; where, he the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> told me, being before the ſaid Earl, he the ſaid Earl told him, That he little thought his Fathers Son would ſerve him ſo as to betray him; and that if he would deſiſt diſcovering what he knew of the Plot, he the ſaid Earl would excuſe him, as to his troubles, and ſave him from appearing at the Court: and that he had ſo ordered Matters with the Judges, that the ſame Bail ſhould ſtand till the next Aſſizes without his appearing; which accordingly was done, to the admiration of all that heard it: And aſſured him, that he the ſaid Earl, would againſt the next Aſſizes, write to or ſpeak with Mr. <hi>Morris</hi> (who ſaid the Earl) is my Friend and your Proſecutor, and order the Matter ſo, that againſt the next Aſſizes, he the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> ſhould be freed.</p>
            <p>After the Aſſizes <hi>Mac Namara</hi> returned home, and <hi>Bourke</hi> being gone away, ſent a Letter to <hi>Mac Namara</hi> for his Linnen and other things left with them: ſaying in his Letter that he was going for <hi>England,</hi> and that the Ship was ready to ſail. <hi>Mac Namara</hi> knowing that it was to inform againſt the ſaid Earl, made all haſte poſſible to him; whom as <hi>Mac Namara</hi> told me, the Earl ordered to ſend for <hi>Bourke,</hi> to prevent his going into <hi>England.</hi> Upon which <hi>Mac Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mara</hi> and his Father-in-law went to <hi>Waterford,</hi> where they found <hi>Bourke,</hi> and told him, that they had a Barrel of Beer which he muſt take part of, and Twenty Shillings in Money for him, but whether the ſaid <hi>Bourke</hi> had the Twenty Shillings, he beſt knows. Vpon which the ſaid <hi>Bourke</hi> came to <hi>Mac Namara</hi>'s houſe, of whoſe come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he made haſte to acquaint the ſaid Earl; and <hi>Mac Namara</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning home, told <hi>Bourke</hi> that the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> deſired to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred unto him; and did aſſure him that the ſaid Earl was not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with him: with many other kind Greetings.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:150258:9"/>
            <p>And being my ſelf at a Chriſtening, in company of <hi>Mac Namara, Bourke,</hi> and others, the Prieſt called <hi>Mac Namara</hi> out, and asked him what was done as to the Buſineſs of the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> at the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes? And ſeeing them go privately under a Bank (to Confeſſing) I asked him what they did there? <hi>Mac Namara</hi> told me that the Prieſt reſolved in Things he doubted of and was troubled about.</p>
            <p>The next day the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> acquainted the ſaid <hi>Bourke</hi> from the Earl, that he had appointed Major <hi>Butler</hi> and <hi>John Rouan</hi> to treat with the ſaid <hi>Bourke;</hi> and that the Earl would give him a Farm and Stock, and what Money he pleaſed, if he would charge Mr. <hi>Villi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars,</hi> Mr. <hi>May,</hi> Captain <hi>Nicholls,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bradly,</hi> and <hi>Peter Anthone,</hi> for imploying him the ſaid <hi>Bourke,</hi> and feeing him unjuſtly to accuſe the ſaid Earl; and ſo to declare that he knew nothing againſt the Earl, but charged him thorow the inſtigation of the Gentlemen aforeſaid: and that thereunto was by them ſubborned, in promiſes of great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Hereupon I asked the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> what would become of <hi>Bourke</hi> then if he ſhould do ſo? He anſwered that then the ſaid Earl would be in the ſame Capacity, or greater than he was before; and then no man could harm him the ſaid <hi>Bourke:</hi> and that the Earl would defend him from any perſon that ſhould endeavour to harm him.</p>
            <p>After which, I talking with <hi>Bourke</hi> concerning the proffers made him, I adviſed him to be juſt, to which he anſwered, That he would rather die than to be unjuſt, but notwithſtanding he would meet the ſaid Gentlemen, to ſee what they would be at. <hi>Mac Namara</hi> alſo told me, That he would requite me, if that I would but intrap Mr. <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> the Earls Steward that was; who had been privy to the Earls Concerns, and might diſcover much againſt the ſaid Earl, if not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</p>
            <p>Some days after <hi>Mac Namara, Bourke,</hi> and I met, being that morning, they went to meet the aforeſaid Major <hi>Butler</hi> and <hi>Rouan,</hi> I being with them at one <hi>James Finican</hi>'s houſe, I again charged <hi>Bourke</hi> to be juſt, and abuſe no man, but to ſpeak the truth; which accordingly he promiſed me to do. And ſo they went from me to the place appointed, where they met the ſaid <hi>Butler</hi> and <hi>Rouan;</hi> who uſed great Reaſonings to perſwade <hi>Bourke</hi> to charge the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men aforeſaid, but could not prevail; as <hi>Mac Namara, Butler,</hi> and <hi>Bourke</hi> told me at their return; who came and lay all together that night at <hi>Mac Namara</hi>'s houſe.</p>
            <p>The next morning I having ſome occaſions at <hi>Waterford,</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor <hi>Butler</hi> going that way, we went together; Major <hi>Butler</hi> telling me that they had treated with Mr. <hi>Bourke</hi> about the Earl of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone</hi>'s Buſineſs, but could not bring him to any thing; the Major wifhing that the Earl had never been born, to intruſt ſuch a one as <hi>Bourke</hi> with a Secret of that importance. I then asked the ſaid Major <hi>Butler</hi> what he thought then would become of it? Who anſwered that he hoped yet to prevail with <hi>Bourke</hi> to do as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>And then <hi>Bourke</hi> writ a Letter to the Earl of <hi>Orrery,</hi> deſiring me to carry the ſame; which I received, having buſineſs that way: In which Letter the ſaid <hi>Bourke</hi> mentioned the ſeveral Treaſons he had to diſcover, but the loſing his Horſe, and the danger he was in of his life, made him uncapable of waiting on the Lord Lieutenant,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150258:10"/>and therefore prayed the Earl of <hi>Orrery</hi> to acquaint the Lord Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of it. Before this Letter was ſent, the Purſivant ſeized the ſaid <hi>Bourke,</hi> and <hi>Mac Namara</hi> ſeized the ſaid Letter and carried it to the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> who acknowledged that he received the ſame. Whereupon I went to <hi>Nicholas Osbourne</hi> Eſquire, one of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Juſtices of the Peace of the ſaid County of <hi>Waterford;</hi> who took part of this Examination which I have now made; and adviſed me to go to the Earl of <hi>Orrery</hi> to impart the whole.</p>
            <p>Vpon the Examination before-mentioned, I adviſed Judge <hi>Keeting,</hi> who took part of my Examinations, that if he ſent privately and apprehended the ſaid perſons, there would be found in <hi>Mac Nama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> his Pocket, a Letter which would confirm the ſubject matter of my Examination, provided the Warrant was committed to — the Execution of a Truſty Perſon; but inſtead thereof the Warrant was ſent to Quarter-maſter <hi>Ely,</hi> before-mentioned, who gave it to the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi>'s Servant; who inſtead of ſearching him, aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, by the ſaid Earls Order, with a Horſe and Neceſſaries for his Journey to the Earls Houſe, where he had from the Earl Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Inſtructions for the Concealing the Treaſon; with great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Rewards from the Earl and the ſaid <hi>Ely:</hi> which accordingly the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> did for ſometime do.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <head>The INFORMATION of John Mac Namara Given in before the Lord Lieutenant and Council and Committees appointed for that Purpoſe.</head>
            <p>WHo ſaith, That <hi>William Bradly</hi> Eſq; one of his Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace for the County of <hi>Waterford,</hi> in the Year 1678, gave me the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> an Oath of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy touching the Plot intended and deſigned in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> and the reſt of the Confederates, againſt the Kings Majeſty: At Which time he imparted to me, That the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Commiſſion from the <hi>French King</hi> to be a Collonel of Horſe in the County of <hi>Waterford;</hi> and that he the ſaid <hi>William Bradly,</hi> was to be his Lieutenant Collonel, and deſired me to provide my ſelf with Horſe and Arms, and to procure as many as I could of thoſe I dare truſt;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150258:10"/>and that I ſhould have a Command of being a Captain under the ſaid Earl and him.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I did provide my ſelf, and ſpoke unto <hi>John Folio, James Finican,</hi> and <hi>Dennis Mac Namara,</hi> to provide themſelves with ſuch neceſſaries as were requiſite for that purpoſe; informing them alſo that Mr. <hi>Bradly</hi> did impart ſuch matters unto me, and who knew that I the ſaid <hi>Mac Namara</hi> had imparted ſuch matters to the ſaid <hi>John James</hi> and <hi>Dennis,</hi> who afterwards did confeſs the ſame to his Grace the Lord Lieutenant and Council, and before I had liberty to ſpeak with them, or they with me, I being then kept cloſe Priſoner from any one of the Kings Evidence.</p>
            <p>The Precedent Examination I gave, when on a Petition preferred by the reſt of the Evidences, I was kept from any of the Earls Friends, and from Quarter Maſter <hi>Ely,</hi> who was always with me before, and not denied to be with me but on the Petition of the aforeſaid Gentlemen: Then it was ordered that I ſhould be kept cloſe and not to have any to come unto me; I was then very fearful to diſcover my mind, becauſe of the Guilt that was upon me, being concerned: Which after a Promiſe of Pardon (if I ſpake the truth) I then reſolved to diſcover ſo far as I knew, though againſt my ſelf; upon which I freely declared my mind in this following Examination.</p>
            <p>After the aforeſaid <hi>William Bradly</hi> did impart to me the aforeſaid Treaſon, I met with the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> on the Lands of <hi>Gave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtown</hi> in the County of <hi>Waterford,</hi> with two of his men, <hi>viz. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Power</hi> his Gentleman and <hi>Garret Mac Teege</hi> his Fowler, and another whoſe name is <hi>Luke Power;</hi> I having in company with me one <hi>William Power</hi> and <hi>Bauſtice Clancy,</hi> being then abroad hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with my Dogs: the ſaid Earl knowing me at a diſtance, called unto me, on which I went unto him. The ſaid Earl taking me aſide from the company, asked me whether Mr. <hi>Bradly</hi> had imparted to me any matter of Secrecy? I replied, He had. The ſaid Earl then told me, That I muſt be very private, and diſcover it to none but thoſe I was very ſure of. After which the ſaid Earl drew a Liſt out of his pocket, and ſhewed me the Names of ſeveral perſons that were to be Superiour Officers, both in the County of <hi>VVaterford,</hi> County of <hi>Corke,</hi> County of <hi>Keery,</hi> County of <hi>Limbrick,</hi> and County of <hi>Cleere,</hi> which I took ſpecial notice of, and knew ſeveral of the Perſons; and amongſt the reſt, the Earl entred my name with my own Pen and Ink in the Liſt; the ſaid Earl telling me he had his Commiſſion ſent him from the French King under Hand and Seal to be a Collonel of a Regiment of Horſe in the County of <hi>VVaterford;</hi> and ſaid that there was hardly a County in <hi>Ireland</hi> (ſave one) but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were appointed by the French King for that purpoſe; and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the County of <hi>Limbricke</hi> Collonel <hi>Pierce Lacy,</hi> the Lord <hi>Brittas,</hi> Sir <hi>John Fitz-Gerrald, David Fitz-Gerrald,</hi> and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>This</hi> Mac Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mara <hi>is the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminants own Name-ſake and Cozen.</hi>
               </note> and in the County of <hi>Cleere John Mac Namara</hi> and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and in the County of <hi>Keery</hi> Sir <hi>Turlo Mac Mahan,</hi> and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others; and others in the County of <hi>Corke:</hi> And that the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> was to be Collonel in the County of <hi>VVaterford,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bradly</hi> to be his Lieutenant Collonel, Quarter-Maſter <hi>Ely</hi> his Major, Mr. <hi>John Butler</hi> Senior his Captain, with the Names of ſeveral others
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150258:11"/>of that County which he did not read unto me. The ſaid Earl ſaying that they were to raiſe ſeveral Hundreds of Men in every County, and that the Superior Officers were to meet on purpoſe to return an exact Account of their Forces to the French King; on which the ſaid King would land many Thouſands of Men at the River <hi>Shannon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>This River</hi> San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non <hi>runs many miles into the Countrey thorow three of the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilleſt Counties in</hi> Ireland; <hi>namely,</hi> Keery, Limbrick, <hi>and</hi> Cleare, <hi>unto the City of</hi> Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, <hi>and will carry great Ships to the ſame from the</hi> Weſt Seas.</note> and as ſoon as they were landed, the next buſineſs was to go to the City of <hi>Limbrick</hi> with five Hundred Men, and divide them into two parts; the one party to enter the City at Candle-light, and that at ſeveral Gates, and ſuch as beſt knew the City were appointed to ſet on the Guards, and put them all to the Sword, the reſt to be hard by the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to enter in immediately when the Allarum was given, and the Body of the Army to draw up as faſt as they could.</p>
            <p>By which ſaid the Earl we do not queſtion, but to poſſeſs our ſelves of the City and <hi>Kings Caſtle,</hi> and to baniſh the <hi>Engliſh</hi> very ſoon; and indeed ſaid the Earl, 'tis the Providence of God to bring ſome downfall on that unjuſt King the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> and his Children, that wronged me in ſo high a Nature on the Account of <hi>Villiars.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid the Earl go home, loſe no time, but make your ſelves ready; for we know not how ſoon occaſion may require your Aſſiſtance, and ſpeak to as many Friends as you can. Which accordingly I did, and provided Arms and Horſes for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>After diſcovery being made hereof by <hi>Hubart Bourke,</hi> as you may read in his Information, who partly knew the proceedings, and having diſcovered the ſame, was bound by Recognizance to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the ſaid Earl at the next Aſſizes at <hi>Waterford;</hi> he did for want of mine and others Teſtimonies, abſent himſelf from the Aſſizes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which he was bound, and for other Reaſons mentioned in his Examination.</p>
            <p>But in a ſhort time after, the Earl hearing that Mr. <hi>Bourke</hi> was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>England,</hi> to make his Application to the King and Parliament; the ſaid Earl commanded me to write unto the ſaid <hi>Bourke,</hi> which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly I did, and ſignified in my Letter, that I would very willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeak with him; but he anſwering not my Expectation, I went my ſelf to him at <hi>Waterford,</hi> and courted him to go along with me home unto my Houſe; which I prevailed with him to do.</p>
            <p>I then haſtned to the ſaid Earl, and gave him an account of my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, which the Earl liked very well. Whereupon he ordered Major <hi>Butler</hi> and <hi>John Rouan</hi> and my ſelf, to confer with the ſaid <hi>Bourke,</hi> and at the Mill of <hi>Carygumier</hi> we met, and according to the ſaid Earls Order, did offer the ſaid <hi>Bourke</hi> a Farm ſtockt, together with a Sum of Money; ſo as that he would charge Mr. <hi>Villiars,</hi> Captain <hi>Nicholls,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bradly,</hi> and others, with ſubborning or prompting the ſaid <hi>Bourke</hi> to proſecute the ſaid Earl, and that he ſhould acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it, and Mr. <hi>Bradly</hi> aforeſaid ſhould confeſs the ſame; and that ſo <hi>Bourke</hi> and <hi>Bradly</hi> ſhould be committed Witneſſes againſt <hi>Villi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars</hi> and <hi>Nicholls:</hi> Upon which the ſaid Earl would bring his Action of. <hi>Scandalum Magnatum</hi> againſt <hi>Villiars</hi> and <hi>Nicholls</hi> of 40000 Pounds; which thing was contrived by Mr. <hi>Andrew Linn</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bradly,</hi> the ſaid Earls Friends: Unto which the ſaid <hi>Bourke</hi> refuſed to conſent.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:150258:11"/>
            <p>Here it is to be obſerved that Mr. <hi>Villiars</hi> and Captain <hi>Nichols</hi> were at Law with the ſaid Earl, and therefore the Earl did ſuppoſe the world would ſconer believe what was lain to their Charge upon the Earls account, though falſely alledged againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bourke</hi> not accepting the aforeſaid proffers, the Earl then petitioned the Lord Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Council, who ſent a Summons for the ſaid <hi>Bourke,</hi> and brought him to <hi>Dublin,</hi> and being examined of ſeveral matters, He gave in his Information, and got alſo Mr. <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ivie</hi> to be ſummoned up, and to be examined, upon whoſe examination; A Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons was iſſued out againſt <hi>Quarter</hi> Mr. <hi>Ely, John Ronan, Maior Butler</hi> aforeſaid, and <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Swillivant</hi> and my ſelf; who were all ſent for to the Council Board. <hi>Quarter</hi> Mr. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> went firſt to the Earls Houſe to have Inſtructions touching the management thereof, the Earl alſo ſent his Gentleman Mr. <hi>Power</hi> for me; I being then in <hi>Waterford,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Power</hi> came to me and told me, that the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> and Quarter Mr. <hi>Ely</hi> ſent for me to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent I might repair to <hi>Doublin,</hi> and having no horſe with me at <hi>Waterford,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Power</hi> the Earls Gentleman provided me with a horſe, on which I went with him to <hi>Curringmore</hi> to the Earls houſe, where I met the ſaid Earl and Quarter Mr. <hi>Ely</hi> together.</p>
            <p>Upon which the ſaid Earl and Quartermaſter <hi>Ely</hi> took me into the Garden, and there did agree to ſend for <hi>John Ronan.</hi> Who came immediately, at which time the Earl and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termaſter <hi>Ely</hi> did inſtruct us what we ſhould ſay, when we came to <hi>Dublin</hi> before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; and told me the great danger, if I ſhould diſcover any thing of the matter, but prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering an Oath unto us, and finding us unwilling to ſwear what they would have us to ſwear the ſaid Earl then told us that we ſhould be abſolved by Dean <hi>Power</hi> his Couſin,
<note place="margin">This <hi>Dean Power</hi> is a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Dean</hi> ſecured by the Earl.</note> and the reſt of the Clergy, and after inſtructing us in the Garden for a conſiderable time, the Earl gave me a horſe, and gave <hi>John Ronan, Lawrence Swillivant</hi> and my ſelf money to bear our char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to <hi>Dublin.</hi> And when we came there we were maintained at the Earls charge, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to get bail for me, if impriſoned: And we were there always accompanied with the Earls Friends, who promiſed me great rewards if I would conceal what I knew. I alſo had Money from Quartermaſter <hi>Ely,</hi> whilſt I was in the Purſivants hands, and ſeveral Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were ſaid in the Country for the Earl and me, whilſt I contained from diſcovering, but ſince have excommunicated me.</p>
            <p>But at length Mr. <hi>Ivie</hi> and Mr. <hi>Samſon</hi> petitioned the Lord Lieutenant and Council to have me kept cloſe Priſoner, and to keep the Earls Friends and Sollicitors from me, which accordingly was done. Now being by my ſelf and conſidering the Evil Caſe I was in, God ſo touched my Conſcience that I confeſſed the Truth.</p>
            <p>Several other things there are relating to the <hi>Powers,</hi> concerning <hi>Stealing of Horſes</hi> and providing of Arms for the ſame purpoſe, which you will find treated of in Mr. <hi>Ivies</hi> Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations and in <hi>James Finicans,</hi> which <hi>Powers</hi> were examined on Oath by Sir <hi>John Davies</hi> and ſince bailed out of Goal by means of Captain <hi>Morris</hi> the Proſecutor, who now goes armed and moſtly accompanied with the Earls Friends and Kindred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>James Finican</hi> was ſolicited by Mr. <hi>Bradly</hi> not to confeſs any thing againſt him the ſaid <hi>Bradly,</hi> for which the ſaid <hi>Bradly</hi> promiſed him a good reward in money, and was before the Committee, and did for ſome time continue to conceal the matter, but being kept from the ſaid <hi>Bradly</hi> for a Seaſon in the <hi>Marſhals</hi> hands, told the ſaid Marſhal that he would not be in Trouble for concealing others Treaſons, he the ſaid <hi>Finican</hi> deſired to be carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain before the Committee confeſſed the whole matter, ſaying that if Mr. <hi>Bradly</hi> were put where he was, he would confeſs the Truth too. This aſtoniſhed the ſaid <hi>Bradly,</hi> for as much the ſaid <hi>Finicans</hi> promiſe to the ſaid <hi>Bradly</hi> of concealing made him the ſaid <hi>Bradly</hi> to tell the Committee, that he would be ſaved by the ſaid <hi>Finicans</hi> Teſtimony.</p>
            <p>You may obſerve alſo, that whilſt I denyed to confeſs the Truth, and to conceal the Plot, the Earls Friends got a petition writ againſt Mr. <hi>Ivie,</hi> to be preferred to the Lord Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Council, <hi>viz.</hi> That the ſaid <hi>Ivie</hi> was a man of ill Fame, and a diſhoneſt man, and that he knew nothing of thoſe Treaſons, and <hi>Briks</hi> before mentioned, which petition they gave me to ſend unto, or deliver unto the Lord Lieut. and Council, in the mean time I being kept from them, my Conſcience forced me to confeſs the Truth; I then ſhewed the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto the ſaid Mr. <hi>Ivie,</hi> of which they were much aſhamed, and would have denyed it, but that I juſtifyed it, and told who brought it unto me, naming Mr. <hi>Michael Row,</hi> the hand alſo being known. Which way J obſerved they always made uſe of to endeavour to clear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by calling in queſtion the reputation of their Accuſers.</p>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:150258:12"/>
               <head>The Examination of <hi>Thomas Sampſon, Gent.</hi> Taken upon Oath at ſeveral times, before the Lord Lieuten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant and Council, and ſeveral Committees, appointed for that purpoſe.</head>
               <p>BEing put to his Oath, <hi>Whether he knew any Treaſons committea by the Earl of</hi> Tyrone, <hi>or ever ſaw any Letters, or ever heard the Earl of</hi> Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone <hi>ſpeak any diſaffected words of the King's Majeſty or Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saith,</hi> That in <hi>March</hi> 1678. The Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> my then Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, was Summoned up before the Lord Lieutenant and Council, upon an Information given in againſt him by one <hi>Habbert Bourke,</hi> who accordingly went and commanded me to wait on the ſaid Earl; and I then believing the ſaid Earl to be abuſed by the ſaid <hi>Bourke:</hi> did (as in duty I thought my ſelf bound) do my utmoſt to ſerve him; and when we came to <hi>Dublin,</hi> to the Inn called the <hi>Pide-horſe,</hi> the Earl ſent me to the <hi>Council-Chamber,</hi> (the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil then ſitting) to Sir <hi>John Davis,</hi> Clerk of the Council; telling me, that Sir <hi>John</hi> was his great friend, and that I ſhould tell him, that the Earl was come to Town, and did earneſtly deſire to ſpeak with him, before that the Council did know that the ſaid Earl was come to Town; on which, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly went to the Council-door, and ſending to Sir <hi>John Davis,</hi> he came forth unto me. After I had delivered my Meſſage, the ſaid Sir <hi>John</hi> told me, that the Council had heard that the Earl was come to Town, and that he thought it the beſt way to acquaint them with it, and that as ſoon as the Council was broke up, he would wait on the Earl, which accordingly he did, and as the ſaid Earl told me, by Order of Council confined him unto his Chamber, where the next day a Committee came to examine him, a Copy of which Examination was allowed the ſaid Earl, which Copy I had, paying for it <hi>nine ſhillings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next night after, I was preſent with Dr. <hi>Moore</hi> (who came into <hi>Ireland</hi> upon Dr. <hi>Oate's</hi> informing againſt him) and was thereupon apprehended and went under Bail. The ſaid <hi>Moore</hi> being at the Earl's houſe at <hi>Curroughmore,</hi> at his coming to <hi>Ireland,</hi> by which I knew him, and was ordered by the ſaid Earl not to keep any Papers or any ſecret from him; and upon the Dr's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation I went with him to the <hi>Sun</hi> Tavern in <hi>Nicholas-Street</hi> in <hi>Dublin,</hi> where he gave me a Bottle of Wine; and entring into diſcourſe with him, he asked me, whether I had read the Earls Examination, I told him, that I had, and that it was in my Chamber, where he might alſo read it; then he asked me, whether I remembred what it was, ſaying, that by the Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I knew what was the Charge againſt the ſaid Earl, and being very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to know what it was, I told him, that the Earl was asked, <hi>whether he did not receive a Letter from one</hi> Robert Power, <hi>who ſtudied the Law at one of the</hi> Inns of Court <hi>at</hi> London, <hi>that mentioned that the</hi> French <hi>had a great ſtroke in</hi> England, <hi>and ſhortly would ſubdue both</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, (or words to that purpoſe.) To which the ſaid <hi>Moore</hi> replied, <hi>was there mention made of that Leetter?</hi> I anſwered <hi>there was,</hi> then ſaid <hi>Moore, we are all undone, my Lord and I too,</hi> ſtrikeing his breaſt and being ſo amazed, lying his head on his hand that he ſpoke not one word for one quarter of an hour.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:150258:12"/>
               <p>Seeing of which I, was not a little moved in my mind, and knowing the private ſittings up at night of the Earl, and Doctor, at the Earls houſe at <hi>Curroughmore,</hi> when he firſt came over, I then concluded, there might be ſome Truth in <hi>Bourk</hi> his Information, and I then reſolved to obſerve matters bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter afterwards, and ſo continued to take notice of the Earls ways and Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations more narrowly.</p>
               <p>Now that the Reader may the better underſtand my Examinations (by the way) I ſhall obſerve ſome Confrontings of the perſons in my Examinations ſpecified before the Committee or perſons by Authority appointed, <hi>viz.</hi> of the ſaid Doctor <hi>Moor,</hi> when I had been examined before Judge <hi>Keeting</hi> the chief Juſtice of the Common Pleas and delivered to him my Examination con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Dr. <hi>Moor</hi> aforeſaid. When I came to the Chief Juſtices houſe, in a little Room by that where we walked the Chief Juſtice and this Dr. <hi>Moor</hi> were ſitting covered, and diſcourſing, as I think, together. And having char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ſaid <hi>Moor</hi> as before, when I was called in, and this Examination read unto him, I told him the ſaid Dr. <hi>Moor, That I was ſure he could not deny ſuch a poſitive Truth,</hi> the Dr. was then ſo amazed that he could not tell what to ſay for himſelf.</p>
               <p>On which, Judge <hi>Keeting</hi> ſaid, <hi>Doctor You are Guilty.</hi> And certainly you being a Doctor of the Civil Law can tell what to ſay for your ſelf, either to confeſs or deny the Fact, Then (ſaid he) after a pauſe, <hi>I</hi> will deny it; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed it, when at the Tavern with me, and when he ſet his hand to the deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of it, his Hand did ſo ſhake, that he was hardly able to write his own Name.</p>
               <p>Of which paſſage <hi>I</hi> told the Lord Lieutenant that night at Council, and Judge <hi>Keeting</hi> owned to his Grace in Council, that He ſaid ſo, and that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the ſaid <hi>Moor</hi> to be guilty, and when <hi>Judg Keeting</hi> demanded Security of the ſaid <hi>Moor,</hi> He told the <hi>Judge,</hi> that he was bound over already, on Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> his Information, and that alſo he was ſecurity for the <hi>EARL</hi> of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All this time <hi>Bourke</hi> was kept cloſe Priſoner, and ordered by the ſaid <hi>Judg</hi> to ſpeak with none, neither have Pen, Ink, nor Paper, But this <hi>Moor</hi> was at Liberty, and never diſarmed, or ever ſince diſarmed or queſtioned, or whether he ever gave any other Bail, I never knew or heard, but went in few days after to the Earls, and I verily do believe, that he went to ſecure the Letters; for I told Judge <hi>Keeting</hi> in what Cupboard of the <hi>Earls</hi> they were.</p>
               <p>But to proceed in my Examination, the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> having given in bail (of which Dr. <hi>Moor</hi> was one) for his appearance the next Term, the Earl then returned home to <hi>Curroughmore,</hi> and one <hi>Thomas Cowdal,</hi> (the aforeſaid <hi>Robert Power</hi> his man) with us. After our return the next Morning, the ſaid Earl commanded me to wait on him to <hi>Coolefine,</hi> a place of the ſaid Earls, one mile from his houſe: where he privately told me, that the ſaid <hi>Cowdal</hi> was to be the next day, on an Inquiry at the Sheriffs Court, to Examin what Eſtate the ſaid Earl had in that County of <hi>Waterford;</hi> in order to ſeize it for the Earl of <hi>Angleſey,</hi> on the pretence of a debt due, from the ſaid, of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> Earl to his Father-in-Law the Earl of <hi>Angleſey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I then asked the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> what would become of me his Steward, when the Lands were made over to the Earl of <hi>Angleſey.</hi> To which the ſaid Earl anſwered, <hi>That it ſhould be never the worſe for me; for what was done, was only to prevent</hi> Bourk's <hi>Charge and</hi> Villiar<hi>'s Judgment, and to preſerve his Eſtate for his Son.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:150258:13"/>
               <p>To which I replyed, that for <hi>Bourke</hi> his Charge, I thought I could clear him, the ſaid Earl of it, to which the ſaid Earl anſwered, that he would give a thouſand pound on that ſcore, for as to <hi>Villiars</hi> his Judgment, he cared not for as much as he had found a way with Captain <hi>Franklin,</hi> and had wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to prove it, ſo that he cared not for him, meaning the ſaid <hi>Villiars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when the Earl returned home to his houſe at <hi>Curroughmore,</hi> He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered me a Copy of a Letter of Atturney, written by the aforeſaid <hi>Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal,</hi> commanding me to copy out the fame in an unknown Character which I did not ordinarily uſe, which I accordingly did, and when I had ſo drawn it, the Earl gave it unto <hi>Cowdal,</hi> which I did, fearing the event, if I had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the Earles Commands.</p>
               <p>The Contents of the ſaid letter of Attorney, were <hi>to impower the ſaid</hi> Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, <hi>to act for the Earl of</hi> Angleſey, <hi>and to receive from the Sheriff the Eſtate when ſeized for the Earl of</hi> Angleſe<hi>'s uſe by the Sheriff.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>According to which, the eftate was ſeiſed, and by the Sheriff delivered to the ſaid <hi>Cowdal,</hi> to the uſe aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>The conſideration of the foregoing Premiſes, together with his forcing me to write the aforeſaid Letter of Attorney, and the End wherefore the ſaid Earl did it, begot in me a thorough belief of the Earles diſaffection to the Goverment, and put me in the mind of many things that were done before, which I thought to have been done in paſſion, which are hereafter mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>About <hi>Christmas</hi> 1678, <hi>William Finch</hi> the ſaid Earles Coachman, a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt,</hi> being at dinner with many more: upon the diſcourſe of disbanding Collonel <hi>Mo Carty</hi>'s Regiment, he then called the Parliament <hi>the ſcum of the Country,</hi> and wiſhing that the ſaid <hi>MoCarty</hi> had all the Parliament Men out one by one, he ſaid, he was ſure he ſaid Collonel <hi>would kick them about the Streets, or if he fought them he would kill them all one by one:</hi> and I adviſing the ſaid <hi>Finch</hi> to talk of things he underſtood, he told me, he knew well what he ſaid, and that he meant the Commons in Parlinment aſſembled; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dinner giving God thanks for our food, concluded ſaying, <hi>God ſave the King,</hi> to which the ſaid <hi>Finch</hi> anſwered, (farting with his mouth) <hi>God bleſs our Church,</hi> meaning, as I believe, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Finch</hi> being a profeſſed <hi>Papist,</hi> and that ſame day at Maſs, all which was done in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of many Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>This was Charged againſt the ſaid <hi>Finch</hi> before the foregoing Judges, at the Aſſizes,
<note place="margin">The Indges were Chief Juſtice <hi>Keeling</hi> and Judge <hi>Reinolls.</hi>
                  </note> but never proſecuted, though I told their Lordſhip, that the ſaid <hi>Finch</hi> was in the houſe where they lay, waiting on the ſaid Earl his Maſter.</p>
               <p>The next day after the ſaid <hi>Finch</hi> ſpoke the aforementioned words, the ſaid Earl laughing at me, told me, <hi>that the ſaid words were not Treaſon,</hi> and did not as much as check the ſaid <hi>Finch</hi> for the ſame. On which, having my Bible in my hand, I ſwore the words before the ſaid Earl, telling him that if it was Treaſon, I would not be guilty of concealing of it.</p>
               <p>Shortly after, the ſaid <hi>Finch</hi> laughed at me, and told me, before ſeveral Witneſſes, <hi>that he now cared not for what he had ſaid against the Parliament, for that now the King had turned them out of doors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I alſo obſerved that the Earl was imploying one Major <hi>Butler,</hi> a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> to perſwade Mr. <hi>Bourk</hi> to deny his information, and to ſay that Collonel <hi>Viliars</hi> and others, did bribe him the ſaid <hi>Bourk</hi> falſly to impeach the ſaid Earl.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:150258:13"/>
               <p>I farther took notice of the Earls allowing all his Papiſt Servants to go to <hi>Maſs;</hi> who when it was forbidden, went at midnight; and of his ſeeming diſpleaſure to them: But in the concluſion, he turned away or ſent to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon all his Proteſtant Servants, as long as he had any. And when I denied his Labourers to work on the Fifth of <hi>November,</hi> he, the ſaid Earl, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to work, calling that day. <hi>A Proteſtant Cheat:</hi> And the day of Humiliation for our late Soveraign of Bleſſed Memory, <hi>The Parliaments Faſt;</hi> ſaying, that he would take the ſin upon him, if I would not keep it.</p>
               <p>I obſerved alſo the great Concourſe of the Officers that came out of <hi>France,</hi> and were disbanded at his houſe: and his Papiſt Servants private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of Papiſts Arms, to ſecure them for their Owners, or other uſes.</p>
               <p>And when Madam <hi>Mortamore</hi> was reading of <hi>Coleman's</hi> Tryal, and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular the long Letter, the Earl ſaid, that what <hi>Coleman</hi> had done was juſt, and that if he had been in <hi>Colemans</hi> place, he would have done as <hi>Coleman</hi> did: I anſwered, that ſuppoſe I was in <hi>Spain,</hi> was it law ful for me to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſubvert the Government there eſtabliſhed? To which the ſaid Earl anſwered, that it was my duty ſo to do, and that there was no Law againſt <hi>Colemans</hi> doing of it in <hi>England;</hi> or for taking away the Kings Life, for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring the ſubverting the Religion, and that <hi>Coleman</hi> ſuffered unjuſtly. And as for <hi>Colemans</hi> endeavouring to Murther the King (ſaid the Earl) that was proved only by two Rogues. And here he ſhewed me a Letter, which, as I remember, came from one <hi>Robert Power</hi> aforeſaid, in which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced a Knight, whoſe Name I do not remember, that begged the Kings Pardon to ſpeak, who after it was granted, told the King, He verily believed that there was no <hi>Plot,</hi> and that the Witneſſes were two Rogues, who if en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, would take away all their Lives. Madam <hi>Mortamor</hi> having end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Saint in Heaven, and that all that had a hand in his Death, were or would be damn'd in Hell.</p>
               <p>At another time the ſaid Earl being appointed by Authority to ſettle the <hi>Militia</hi> with the High Sheriff <hi>William Dobbins</hi> Eſq; and others, Mr. <hi>Fith Gerrald</hi> of <hi>Waterford</hi> ſent to him to act in it: and I my ſelf carried the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from the ſaid <hi>Fith Gerrald</hi> to him, telling him the ſaid Earl, that by his appearing, and ſhewing himſelf active for the King, he might again redeem the Kings Favour, and do himſelf and Servants good. To which the Earl re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, That if the <hi>French</hi> were at <hi>Coole-ſin,</hi> meaning a place a mile from his houſe, he would not draw his Sword againſt them.</p>
               <p>And at another time when he wanted Oats for his Horſes, the Earl laid, That he had rather want Bread for his Table, than Oats for his Horſes, not knowing how ſoon he might be called on Service. Now having denied the ſerving of his own King before, I might well wonder whom he intended to ſerve, having made ſuch Great Proviſion of Horſes.</p>
               <p>And afterwards when perſwaded to go and meet the Sheriff about the <hi>Militia,</hi> he went to a place called the <hi>Three Miles Bridge</hi> in the County of <hi>Waterford,</hi> where the meeting was appointed; but juſt met them and made haſte back, and disheartned thoſe he met from going; and jeared at the Troop, calling it the <hi>Buttermilk-Troop,</hi> ſaying that his <hi>Great Horſe</hi> would beat a Troop of them. At his return ſeveral of the Officers that came out of <hi>France</hi> were come to the ſaid Earl's Houſe, where he met them.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:150258:14"/>
               <p>And at another time having had ſome Trial-gone againſt him in the Courts at <hi>Dublin;</hi> and receiving a Letter from his Attorney or Sollicitor, of ſomething which the King had done concerning it in <hi>England,</hi> he fell into a great Paſſion againſt the King, and ſaid, That if the King was pulled out of his Throne, he would not draw his Sword to defend him.</p>
               <p>And upon getting one <hi>Owen Whelan</hi> an Old Tory, and making him his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant or Bayliff, I telling him that the Country would take notice of it, he wiſhed that he had ten thouſand ſuch Torys, for there is a time coming, ſaid he, that I could make uſe of them.</p>
               <p>Obſerving all thoſe things, it made me uſe all poſſible means to get my ſelf free from the ſaid Earl's Service; and in order thereunto got one Mr. <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Claſmore,</hi> being the Earl's Kinſman, to ſpeak to the Earl; who was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon appointed to audit my Accompts, which accordingly he did. After which they uſed all means and endeavours to take away my good Name or Life, <hi>viz. Garret M. Teege</hi> alias <hi>Wall,</hi> the Earls Fowler, who threatned my life, lying in wait for me with one of the Earls beff Guns, (as he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, And at a Fair at <hi>Clonagan</hi> he lent one <hi>Martha M. Shehan</hi> a Knife, which the ſaid <hi>Shehan</hi> had ready to kill me withal, had not one eſpying of it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented him by taking the Knife from him, as he was giving the Stab, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured it. Hereupon I acquainted the Earl therewith, who deſired to ſee the Knife, and taking it into his hands, broke it, and then bid me to proſecute the Offenders.</p>
               <p>At the fame time the aforeſaid <hi>Owen Whelan</hi> the Old Tory, and others lay in wait for me with Clubs, which was alſo diſcovered, and prevented by my preſenting a Piſtol at them, and ſo made my eſcape from them.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>John Power,</hi> who, as the Servants told me, killed the Lord <hi>Mohan,</hi> threatned my Life: he was carried to <hi>Dublin</hi> in the Earls Coach, and there kept private at the Earls Charge.</p>
               <p>Lieutenant <hi>Thomas Power</hi> the Earl's Kinſman, now of Captain <hi>Congroſe</hi>'s Company, alſo threatned my life at the Aſſizes in the Judges Chamber. He alſo got me to be ſued by one <hi>Porter,</hi> a Papiſt, for Wine, which the ſaid Earl had many years before I came unto him; the ſaid <hi>Power</hi> wiſhing that he had broke my Neck when he laſt met me, for then, ſaid he, you would not have been an Informer now. This was after I denied the Earl's Man to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear for the Ear againſt the aforeſaid Mr. <hi>Bourke.</hi> And having had Warrants from <hi>William Bradly,</hi> Eſq; againſt all the aforeſaid Perſons, got by the Earls pretended leave to me; yet afterwards they were all ſecured from Juſtice by the ſaid Earl. Of which I acquainted the Judges of the Aſſizes, but they gave me no Warrant againſt the ſaid Perſons; but afterwards acquainting the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Booth</hi> therewith, he gave his Warrant againſt them; but it could not be ſerved, the Offenders being all ſecured from Juſtice by the ſaid Earl in his own houſe or lands.</p>
               <p>Madam <hi>Mortamore</hi> telling me, That if I proſecuted them, eſpecially the <hi>Powers,</hi> that I ſhould loſe my life, and no body know what was become of me, being a ſtranger in the Country</p>
               <p>And when Mr. <hi>Bourke</hi> was to proſecute the ſaid Earl at the Aſſizes at <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terford, Auguſt</hi> 14. 1679. fear cauſing him not to appear, <hi>Thomas Power,</hi> the Earls Gentleman came to me and told me, that the Earl would have me to appear for him before the Judges; and that if I would ſo appear for him the Earl would be clear'd: <hi>Bourke</hi> being gone with promiſes of Reward, if I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150258:14"/>would ſo appear, which I refuſing to do, the ſaid <hi>Power</hi> parted from me in a threatning manner, and afterwards at Mr. <hi>Bradlys</hi> was followed by <hi>Finch</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid and others.</p>
               <p>The ſame night Mr. <hi>Dobbins</hi> the High Sheriff was ſent by the Judges for me to come to them to their Chamber, which I accordingly did, at which time the Judges told me, that the aforeſaid <hi>Bourke</hi> was gone, and had ſent them a Letter, wherein he mentioned, that fear and want of his Evidence, made him to abſcond, or words to that purpoſe. Then the Judges ſent for Mr. <hi>Mo Cartee</hi> the Deputy Clerk of the Crown, and for <hi>Bourk's</hi> Information, who brought it, and read it nnto me before the Judges, and hearing them read, I told the Judges, that as for part of the information, as it was read un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me. I thought the Earl not guilty; but as to <hi>Powers</hi> Letter, I refuſed to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thereto, and the reaſon I anſwered ſo, was, becauſe I was not on my Oath, and therefore conſidering the danger I was in, being ſo threatned, as before, and ſeeing the Judges and the ſaid Earl, lodging and eating together, and the Earles ſervants at the Judges door, as if they had been keepers of the door, cauſed me then to confeſs nothing againſt the Earl, of what I knew.</p>
               <p>The Judges commended me for a very honeſt man, as they told me that they heard I was, and therefore, <hi>Bourke</hi> being gone, if I would vouch for the Earl, that he was not concerned in any thing that he was charged, the ſaid Judges ſaid that on my bare averring it, the ſaid Earl would be acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I then complained much againſt the Earles Servants; eſpecially, againſt the aforeſaid <hi>Finch,</hi> (who was then in the houſe) and ſo I left the Judges; who ſent for me a ſecond time, and Judge <hi>Keeling</hi> asked me; <hi>whether I had any Treaſons, or knew any thing of the Earles diſaffection to the King, to inform them withal;</hi> I being ſilent they concluded I had, and therefore command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me to bring the ſame in writing, to them the next morning, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, I promiſed them to do. But having acquainted the Judges of the ſaid <hi>Finch,</hi> as you may read before, and of his being in the Town, and he not being apprehended; and being in the Judges own Chamber, where they dined with the Earl, ſolicited and threatned by <hi>Mr. Shortnal,</hi> the Earles pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Chaplain, and menac'd and threatned, as before, by the aforeſaid Lieutenant <hi>Thomas Power,</hi> in the Judges Chamber; and in open Court by <hi>William Buckner,</hi> the Earles Attorney, before the Judges; and knowing the great Correſpondency there was betwixt the Earland the Chief Juſtice <hi>Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling;</hi> and the great dealings there had been betwixt Judge <hi>Reinolls</hi> and him, the Earl often telling his great joy when Mr. <hi>Keeling</hi> was made Chief Juſtice, ſaying, when the aforeſaid <hi>Cowdal</hi> brought him the news thereof, that now <hi>he,</hi> the ſaid Earl, <hi>neither feared the Lord Lieutenant, nor Lord Chancelour his enemie,</hi> and that <hi>he cared not now where he was tryed,</hi> having before often ſaid, that <hi>he could not be forced to</hi> England <hi>to be tryed, and that in</hi> Ireland <hi>they could not, without calling a Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The conſideraton whereof, and the fear I was in to deal with ſo potent a perſon, made me not to appear according to my promiſe, the next Morning, to give in my teſtimony; but I went into the County of <hi>Cark</hi> to adviſe with the Earl of <hi>Orrery,</hi> whom I knew would adviſe me, whoſe ſickneſs hindred my procedure, until I was ſent for by the Lord Lieutenant and Council, and being there ſeveral times examined, and by ſeveral Councils and Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, that our genuine ſence might be taken, and for that prevention of all miſtakes, Mr. <hi>Bourke, Mr. Ivy</hi> and my ſelf, gave in thoſe forementioned Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150258:15"/>
               <p>In which I alſo acquainted the Lord <hi>Lieutenant</hi> and <hi>Council</hi> that one <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Swillivan,</hi> a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> left with the Earl by a Prieſt, and afterwards made the Earles Butler, was in <hi>March</hi> 1678, allowed to go, or was ſent, into the County of <hi>Keery,</hi> under pretence of ſeeing his Friends there, who went his journey thither as the Earl went firſt to <hi>Dublin,</hi> after he the ſaid Earl was impeached by <hi>Bourke.</hi> After his return I heard him talk much of Sir <hi>John Fitz Gerald</hi> and others, in the County of <hi>Limbrick,</hi> and telling me how much he was made by the ſaid Gentlemen, whom I after ſaw taxed for like Treaſon by <hi>Mr. David Fitz Gerald,</hi> and obſerving alſo the return of the Earl from <hi>Dublin,</hi> and he from his journey the ſame time, and the Earles repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him with a kick before me, and withal, giving him a wink, and went into private together a conſiderable time, by which I ſaw that the Earles an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger was but pretended to him.</p>
               <p>Upon which the ſaid <hi>Swillivant</hi> being examined by the Biſhop of <hi>Meath</hi> and Sir <hi>John Davis</hi> a Committee, at which time Sir <hi>John Davis</hi> read my Examination or Information to him, before me who was appointed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front him; he confeſſed he were with the Gentleman Sir <hi>John Fith Gerrald</hi> and ſome of them accuſed, who made much of him; but the ſaid Sir <hi>John Davis</hi> ſo much threatned me and upheld the ſaid <hi>Swillivant,</hi> that they made nothing of it, always obſerving that Sir <hi>John Davis</hi> had more care to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine or to intrap us, then to intrap the Impeached; elſe they might have ſent and examined the Earls Cupboard where his Letters lay, which would put all things out of diſpute, as I told Judge <hi>Keeting</hi> and Sir <hi>John Davis,</hi> and fully ſatisfied them whether our Teſtimony was true or no.</p>
               <p>All theſe precedent Examinations and Informations together with three more, <hi>viz. Dennis Mac Nemara, John Foley,</hi> and <hi>James Finican,</hi> all agreeing in their Evidence with thoſe Examinations &amp; Informations, notwithſtanding the one did not know what the other had confeſſed or declared All which Examinations and Informations being delivered to the Lord <hi>Lieutenant</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> we were all bound to appear at <hi>Waterford</hi> Aſſizes, to proſecute the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone:</hi> Where we accordingly went, having firſt petitioned the Lord <hi>Lieutenant</hi> and <hi>Council</hi> that none of the Earls Kindred, Papiſt, or Tenants ſhould be of the Jury: Acquainting his Grace, that if they were not exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from being of the Jury, it was in vain for any of the Kings Evidence to appear there: Which Petition the Lord <hi>Lieutenant</hi> told us was granted; but when we came to the Aſſizes, we found it denied by the Judges: and the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Proceeding were ſuch as made the Evidence complain, ſome unto the Kings Majeſty, and others to the Lord Lieutenant and Council.</p>
               <p>Upon which <hi>Thomas Samſon,</hi> one of the Examinants was commanded by the Lord Lieutenant to deliver his knowledge in writing into the Council of the Proceedings againſt the ſaid Earl at the Aſſizes: Which he accordingly did in the following Examination. On which the Lord Lieutenant and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, telling the ſaid <hi>Sampſon,</hi> the ſaid Examination was to be ſent to the Kings Majeſty. And to vindicate my Reputation, the Lord Lieutenant and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil was pleaſed to give me leave to come for <hi>England,</hi> and gave me their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150258:15"/>
               <head>The Examination of <hi>Thomas Samſon</hi> Gent. taken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord Lieutenant and Council of <hi>Ireland</hi> the <hi>14.</hi> of <hi>May 1680,</hi> by the Lord Lieutenants ſpecial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, about the Tryal of the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and <hi>William Bradley</hi> Eſq; at <hi>VVaterford</hi> Aſſizes, and the Juries Proceedings therein.</head>
               <p>WHo ſaith, That according to my Recognizance I went to the ſaid Aſſizes on the 10. of <hi>March</hi> laſt paſt; the then going Judges being Sir <hi>Richard Reynolls</hi> and Sir <hi>William Davis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next morning after my arrival there, I waited on them in their Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to receive their Commands. I then told Judge <hi>Reynolls,</hi> that I had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time before petitioned the <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> That no Papiſts, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, or Kindred ſhould be of the Jury: and that his Grace told me, that my Petition was anſwered, and that he would give the going Judges Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions therein.</p>
               <p>To which Judge <hi>Reynolls</hi> replied, That all the Judges had given their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that it was contrary to Law, that Papiſts ſhould be exempted of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Jury. I then anſwered, that I was content with what my Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours thought fit.</p>
               <p>Judge <hi>Reynolls</hi> then told me I might have a Councel allowed me, I told him, I deſired it in regard it was for the King, and by reaſon I was a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to ſuch Proceedings: Upon which I made choice of Counſellor <hi>Becket,</hi> but Judge <hi>Davis</hi> told me that he was not acquainted with Crown Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and therefore ſaid, they would allow me Counſellor <hi>Pine;</hi> and that they would give me a Note to him; but they went to Church, and gave me no note at all. I then went to enquire for Councellor <hi>Pine,</hi> but found that he was not in, or near the Town.</p>
               <p>Judge <hi>Reynolls</hi> alſo told me, That the Earl was to be indicted for High Treaſon, and that Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> was to be indicted with him on the ſame Bill.</p>
               <p>I then replyed, that I much wondred at it, in regard that the Witneſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the one, were not againſt the other.</p>
               <p>And that I thought Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> might, if well handled, and indicted aſun der, be a material Witneſs for the King; but Judge <hi>Reynolls</hi> then anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it was ſo ordered above: I then ſaid, I was content with what Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity commanded. Upon which the Judges went to Church, from whence they returned to the Court, and after the Ceremony of the Court uſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Grand Jury was called: Counſellor <hi>Porter,</hi> a Papiſt, ſaid, My Lord, there is a Peer of the Nation in queſtion, and therefore he prayed leave to appear for him. I anſwered, That there were three Nations in the Caſe, and that the Kings Witneſs had rather need of Counſel: Yet the Judges allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Counſellor <hi>Porter</hi> to ſpeak, and Counſellor <hi>Longan,</hi> a Papiſt alſo; who ſaid, My Lord, I am for the Impeached: And they prayed leave to except a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſome of the Jury, which was againſt none but Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>The two Counſels together with three Attorneys appeared for the Earl, the Kings Evidence being not allowed one: and preſſing for a Counſel, Judge
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150258:16"/>
                  <hi>Reynolls</hi> anſwered me, he would be our Counſel; which I took as ſpoken in deriſion.</p>
               <p>Hereupon I deſired to object againſt Tenants and Kindred of the Earſ's, Papiſts being before allowed; and in particular againſt <hi>Paul Sherlock,</hi> a Tenant, and <hi>Peirce Welch</hi> Gent a Kinſman of the Earl, and others, who upon their bare denying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Tenants or Kindred, were admitted Jurors, and ſworn; whereas they were both either Tenants or Kindred. After Dinner I attended the Judges again in their Chamber, who ſwore me and the other Witneſſes, commanding us to attend the Grand Jury; which we accordingly did, waiting in a Chamber next the Grand-Jury Chamber; and <hi>Hubbart Bourke</hi> one of the Evidences, went to the Jury, and intreated Admittance, and deſired to be heard, as he told me and the reſt of the Witneſſes. But the Jury told him, that they had his Examinations already, and that they had no buſineſs with any of us; for that they were ordered to hear no new Matters: To which I anſwered, That I was ſworn to attend the Jury, and therefore would have Admittance.</p>
               <p>Capt. <hi>Grant</hi> always meeting the Evidence at the Door, and telling them that they had no buſineſs with us, which was unknown to ſome of the Jury.</p>
               <p>Whereupon I went three times to the Grand-Jury-Door, and being earneſt, I was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in; Capt. <hi>Grant</hi> and Mr. <hi>Carew</hi> asked me, Whether I had any new Treaſons to inform the Jury of, other than what were delivered in before the Lord Lieutenant and Council in my Examinations? and told me, if I had, they were ordered not to hear (or Words to that purpoſe;) I told them, that I had no new matter but what had been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord Lieutenant and Council; but I deſired to have my Examinations read unto me, to ſee if they were all there, or if need required, that I might explain the ſame, or words to that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>On which, they read one of my Examinations unto me, whereby I found all my Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were not there; or at leaſt read unto me, of which I informed the Jury.</p>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>Welch,</hi> Capt. <hi>Grant,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Carew</hi> preſſed not to have me heard; on which, I told them, that ſome of them were fitter to be on an Examination, than on that Jury; on which they were ſilent.</p>
               <p>And the Foreman acknowledged before the Committe of the Council appointed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine them, that they received but Nine Examinations; of which he gave me an Account in writing, and that I told them of ſeveral things that were not in thoſe Examinations.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>John Davis</hi> wondering where the fault lay, that all the Examinations had not been delivered to the Jury, being not the one half of the Examinations taken before the Lord Lieutenant and Councel, and alſo of the leaſt value, the next day, being in the Judges Chamber, there came in Capt. <hi>Grant</hi> and Major <hi>Richard,</hi> two of the Jury, who told Judge <hi>Reynolls,</hi> that the Bill againſt the ſaid Earl, was found <hi>Ignoramus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereupon Judge <hi>Reynolls</hi> asked Maj. <hi>Richard,</hi> whether they all agreed to it? He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That 7 were for finding the Bill, and 10 againſt it, and ſo they were out-voted.</p>
               <p>Capt. <hi>Grant</hi> ſaying that they found the Matter Charged againſt the ſaid Earl High Treaſon, but they invalidated the Teſtimony of the Witneſſes, and that was the reaſon why they did not find the Bill. But being asked, Whether he knew or heard of any evil Report of me? he denied that ever he did. And not long before, Capt. <hi>Grant,</hi> and they that were againſt finding the Bill, gave a Teſtimony under all their hands for one of the Evidence's Honeſty, which is ready to be produced; it being at a time when he appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Earl, and alſo promiſed him Bribes if he would not confeſs. And when three of the Jury that were for finding the Bill, and three that were againſt it, were ſummon'd before the Councel, the Foreman ſaid, That the nine Examinations in their hands were ſufflcient for any to find the Bill; but he was ſure that if there were as many more, and as many more Witneſſes, yet they that were againſt it, would not have conſented to the finding of it.</p>
               <p>But that which I further obſerved, was, That after the Evidence were ſome of them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied Allowance to the Jury, being told, that they had Evidence enough before them; on which the Evidence left attending, and were gone: They then pretended that they ſent for them, and not finding them, informed the Judges, that they would have heard them, but could not find them: I deſired that Mr. <hi>Mac Nemara</hi> might be examined to this; but was not when I came away.</p>
               <p>The next day, being on my Duty, attending the Court, the Bill was brought in <hi>Ignora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus;</hi> on which I told the Judges, that I obſerved but juſt before, a Bill was found againſt a Perſon for pulling a poor Fellow out of a Smoky Cabben, for which a Fine of 4 <hi>d.</hi> was impoſed.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:150258:16"/>
               <p>But the King (ſaid I) had hard meaſure that a Bill ſhould not be found againſt a perſon for denying to be aſſiſtant to him if he were pulled out of his Throne, with other Crimes ſworn againſt him. And therefore I prayed the Judges that the Jury might be ſent for and poled, and that they might anſwer one by one, which were for finding the Bill, and which againſt it. And that inquiry might be made of the perſons that were of moſt value as to the Kings Intereſt, and proteſtant Religion, they that voted for finding the Bill, or they that voted againſt it.</p>
               <p>On which the Judges ſent for the Jury, and had them called over one by one, and no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was put to them, but <hi>whether they were all agreed?</hi> To which the Foreman anſwered, That according to the way they uſually uſed in Juries (that is) by Poles or moſt Voices they were agreed, but no otherwiſe: But if it were according to law, they left that to the Judges; and ſo the Bill was received <hi>Ignoramus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I alſo told the Judges in open Court, That one <hi>John Winſton,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Tyrone's</hi> Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchal, and the laſt Subſheriff of whom I had informed the Lord Lieutenant and Council, That what private concernes came to the ſaid Sheriffs hands, the ſaid Earl ſhould be firſt acquain ted therewith.</p>
               <p>On which his Grace ordered in Council, that he ſhould be no more Subſheriff: yet as ſoon as another High Sheriff was choſen, the ſaid <hi>Winſton</hi> deſired to be Subſheriff, and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto offered the High Sheriff, That if he would admit of him the ſaid <hi>Winſton</hi> to be Subſheriff, and let the Pannel of the Old Sheriff ſtand, the aforeſaid Counſellor <hi>Porter</hi> ſhould give him Counſel all the Year for nothing: And that Mr. <hi>Andrew Lynn,</hi> and he late High Sheriff ſhould be his Friend for ever; Of which I offered the Judges Proof in Court, Witneſſes being there ready to atteſt it: But the Judges took no notice of it.</p>
               <p>There was likewiſe brought to the Judges by Maj. <hi>Rickards,</hi> an accuſation of one <hi>Francis Hatchet</hi> againſt the ſaid Earl, for that the ſaid Earl would have imployed him to make Pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaves and Holbard-ſtaves, and that the ſaid Earl ſhewed him heads to put thereon; of which the Judges commanded me to give in writing what I knew of the ſame; which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly I did, and was ſworn unto it, but was ordered by the Judges, not to ſpeak with the ſaid <hi>Hatchet.</hi> I then told the Judges, that I ſcorned to do any thing under hand: The the ſaid <hi>Hatchet</hi> was ordered to be examined by Major <hi>Richards,</hi> who when he was exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined again, minced his Teſtimony, from what he had ſaid before, to the ſaid Major <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards,</hi> alledging, that he dare not ſpeak more for fear of his life, or firing his houſe. When Major <hi>Richards</hi> was examined to this by the Committee appointed therefore, Sir <hi>John Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis</hi> being one of the then Committee, ſaid, he wondred that this Examination ſhould net be delivered to the Lord Lientenant and Council by Judge <hi>Reinolls,</hi> who received it, in as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as he thought it one of the moſt material things that came in againſt the ſaid Earl, of which, I being thereunto, required a Copy I gave to the Council of which things the Earl was not accuſed of before, but for fear he ſhould be the workman that was to make the aforeſaid ſtaves with the ſaid <hi>Hatchet,</hi> (but could not by reaſon none of the Earles Timber would not make them) did give a Note under his Hand and Seal, that the Earl did not intend them for any plotting againſt the King, but for his own uſe. And when I went to Judge <hi>Reinolls</hi> his Chamber, to take my leave of him, I was an hour with him in private, before Judge <hi>Davis</hi> came to him, this I did auer, notwithſtanding Judge <hi>Davis</hi> did acquaint his Grace the Lord Lieutenant, that they agreed when they firſt came the Circuit, not to be aſunder when any of us (meaning the Kings Evidence) were before them.</p>
               <p>They told the Lord Lieutenant ſo when I confronted the Judges at the Council with this following Diſcourſe, and about the Proceedings at the Aſſizes.</p>
               <p>I alſo told Judge <hi>Reinolls,</hi> when I was at his Chamber to take my leave of him, that Sir <hi>Thomas Osborn</hi> one of the Jury ſaid, that had the like Evidence, Againſt his father as againſt the Earl, he would have found the Bill, which he did not deny when examined before the Committee.</p>
               <p>Judge <hi>Reynolls</hi> then told me that the Earl had better given a 1000 <hi>l.</hi> than that the Bill ſhould have been brought in <hi>ignoramus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when I told Judge <hi>Reinolls</hi> that Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> who was joyned in the ſame Bill with the Earl, would have confeſſed what he knew, and gave a great diſcovery to the thing.</p>
               <p>Judge <hi>Reinolls</hi> anſwered, that if he had confeſſed any thing, he would have hanged him as round as a <hi>Juglers Box.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150258:17"/>
               <p>And I moſt humbly acquainted the Lord <hi>Lieutenant,</hi> that the Bill being not found againſt the Earl, moſt men looked upon us as ruined, who were the Witneſſes for His Majeſty, and they that can act moſt againſt us, account themſelves moſt happy.</p>
               <p>Many perſons having ſaid from the firſt, that if we diſcovered any thing, we were ruined in regard all the great Ones of the Nation would be againſt us.</p>
               <p>And on inquiry, it will be proved that ſeven of the ten of the Jury that found the Bill <hi>ignoramus,</hi> were Kindred, Tenants and friends of the Earles pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the purpoſe,</p>
               <p>One of them allyed to Mr. <hi>Bradley,</hi> was brought out of another County to make a body in the County of <hi>Waterford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as to ſeveral preparations made in Coffee Houſes to aſperſe the Kings Evidence, I am ready to make out the perſons whom, the time when, and the places where.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>The Copy of the JURORS Names.</head>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Theſe were for finding the Bill.</head>
                        <item>William Bolton <hi>Ar.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Andrew Rickard, <hi>Ar.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Thomas Osbourne, <hi>Kt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>John Morris, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Robert Whitley, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>John Stevens, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Henry Jaques, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Theſe for not finding the Bill.</head>
                        <item>Jeſpr. Grant, <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Pierce Welch, <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Thomas Kneal, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Robert Cooke, <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Robert Carew, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Michael Carew, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Roger Carew, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Paul Sherlocke, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>James Oldfield, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Alphon O Bryan, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="queries">
               <head>Several Queries touching the Earl of <hi>Tyrone's</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi>'s Tryals.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WHether all the Examinations taken againſt the ſaid Perſons, or any of them, before the Lord Lieutenant and Council, on which the Lord Lieutenant and Council, declared the ſaid Earl's to be High Treaſon, ſhould not have been delivered to the Jury.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether the Evidence for the King ought not to be heard by the Jury, when ſworn thereunto.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether the Kings Witneſſes-ought not to have one Counſel, as well as the Accuſed five Counſels and Attorneys.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether the Bill could be found <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> twelve not agreeing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether all thoſe Letters mentioned in the Examinations ſhould not be ſearched for, when deſired by the Evidences, to ſtrengthen the Evidence, and told the place where they might be found.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whether the ſame perſons were not fit Evidences for the King on their Oaths, when proffered to clear the Accuſed on their bare Word.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Whether all that was charged ſhould not be examined and diſarmed.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Whether a Perſon accuſed for feveral Treaſons, on Tryal of ſome, can be cleared of all, meaning when all Examinations and Witneſſes were not heard, or known of by the Jury, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:150258:17"/>
               <head>The Account and Vindication of the above-mentioned Mr. <hi>Hubbart Bourke</hi> his Perſon and Family.</head>
               <p>LEſt the unworthineſs of my Perſon, and ſmalneſs of my Fortune, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the many Lies and Falſhoods which do ordinarily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſuch as come on the Stage, wherein great perſons are concerned, thereby to weaken or invalidate their Teſtimony, (the accuſed having little elſe to excuſe their fact, as will evidently appear in Mr. <hi>Sampſons</hi> Examination, and his Confronting the Jury) for fear, I ſay, leſt the one or the other ſhould leſſen the circumſpection or care of all Proteſtants, to avoid that fire, which through the warning of Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> and others, hath yet been ſuppreſſed, and which without care may yet break forth into a greater flame; we have therefore apart at the end of all our Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations annexed a ſhort excuſe for our preſumption, and alſo given a brief deſcription of our ſelves.</p>
               <p>As to my birth, I was born in <hi>Tomound,</hi> Son to <hi>Edmond Bourke,</hi> a man of honeſt life, though not the richeſt of his name. I had my Breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Education in the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the Romiſh Religion, and alſo under an Atturney, which employ ſince I have been at my own diſpoſe, hath maintained me, by keeping of Courts in the Country, and acting as an Atturney in the ſame. And whereas it hath been generally ſaid by ſome, who make it their buſineſs to invalidate my Teſtimonie, out of love to the Impeached, that the reaſon why I informed againſt the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> is, for that he ſent me to Goal for great Miſdemeanours; what cauſe he had of ſending me to Goal, did appear before the Judges of the Aſſizes to be very unjuſt, there being nothing at the Aſſizes laid to my Charge, or on the Indictment proved; but I hereby declare, that my being in Goal, together with the miſcarriage of my Letters ſent to his Grace the Lord Lieutenant, was the only reaſon why I did not diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the things contained in my Examination ſooner; and that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of my Conſcience to God, and Allegiance to my King, was the only motive thereunto. And to make it more evident, ſeeing the evil of my former Religion, and being convinced in my Conſcience that no ſound Religion can be maintained by the effuſion of innocent blood, diſobedience to Superiours, and ſubverting of Government; I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have before his Grace the Lord Primate and Chancellour of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and hereby do declare to all others, my ſelf to be of the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> and by Gods aſſiſtance do intend to live and die in the ſame; and I deſire all perſons to conſider, for what I leave my Friends and Relations, and Name-ſakes, denying my ſelf ſuch great proffers and advantages, as by my Information you may ſee I have refuſed. And I do hereby further declare, in the preſence of Almighty God, that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver directlie or indirectlie received any Sum or Sums of Money, or to the value of one Meals Meat, or ever in the leaſt expect ſo to do, from any of the Gentlemen on whom I was deſired to charge that I ſhould be by them hired to Impeach the ſaid Earl, and then I ſhould have ſuch large Rewards. If the world will but conſider the great hardſhips I have lain under, to be impriſoned ſo long time, in a Countrey where I have no Friends, or at leaſt, that dared to appear for me, and on ſo unjuſt a cauſe as the Judges and Jury were ſenſible it was, when I by them was acquitted;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150258:18"/>I know they will conclude I had very hard meaſure. And when I was ſent for to give my Teſtimony for the King, being then but one ſingle Teſtimony that appeared, and had onely Truth and Juſtice to ſtand by me, I was by the malice of the Sheriff, or Sub-Sheriff, bound with cords under the Horſes belly, contrary to the Warrant ſent for me by the Lord Lieutenant and Councel; and after I was brought to <hi>Dublin,</hi> I was falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Indicted for horſe-ſtealing, by the Earl of <hi>Tyrones</hi> Atturney, and by the Judges of the Kings-Bench Acquitted; and when I was bound over to <hi>Waterford</hi> to proſecute the ſaid Earl, was therefrom afrighted by Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces and Threatnings, and afterwards made a ſpectacle of Contempt, being carried about with my legs tyed in an egregious manner, by the Earls ſervants, under a falſe pretence of the Lord Lieutenants Warrant, who ſaid he granted no ſuch Warrant. And when I deſired that Mr. <hi>Sampſon</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ivie</hi> might be ſent for, knowing that Mr. <hi>Ivie</hi> could, and believing that Mr. <hi>Sampſon</hi> muſt of neceſſity know of the Treaſon, when they came up I was ordered to have neither Pen, Ink, nor Paper, nor to ſpeak with any out of the Purſivants ſight and hearing, until they were fully examined apart; notwithſtanding all perſons that were ſent for on our charging them, were never kept aſunder, but one left to inform the other, until we acquainted the Lord Lieutenant and Council there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. Conſidering the premiſes, I do deſire all good Chriſtians to be ſparing in their judging of me for what I have done, God of his mercy having raiſed me up (with others) to make a diſcovery of what in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability might have inflamed the whole Nation: and let not the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of my duty in diſcovering, though the preſent danger ſeem to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenc'd, be any diſreputation to the Diſcoverer, who is ready to ſerve God, his King and Country, to the utmoſt of his power.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Hubbart Bourke.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>An Account of Mr. <hi>Macnemarrah.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Now to follow the ſame method which the other Evidence hath done before, being ſo very well known in the Countrie both by name and living, I ſhall therefore trouble my ſelf the leſs, and onely tell you, that I am of the <hi>Macnemarrahs</hi> of <hi>Cracolo,</hi> and was for many years a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and never a Papiſt but ſince I married into a Popiſh Family in the County of <hi>Waterford,</hi> and have lived there ſome years paſt; and having never ſince I lived there been excluded from being of the Grand or Pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Jurie of every Aſſizes, and all along been of good Credit with the beſt of the Countrie; often employed in publick Concerns, and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver of the Kings Revenue of Hearth-money in ſeveral Counties; which Office I have faithfully and honeſtly diſcharged: ſo that I defie any man to charge me to the coutrarie, being at moſt References or Countrie-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns made uſe of, either publick or private.</p>
               <p>And when the Powers mentioned in Mr. <hi>Ivie</hi>'s Examination, who was concerned with me in that Plot, were apprehended by a Lieutenant's Warrant (who after they were apprehended fled from Juſtice) I was alſo apprehended, and gave Bail, but kept from trial by the Earls intereſt with the Proſecutors. At which time many of the Jurie and other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen gave a Certificate of my good behaviour, and ſpoke for me in open Court, though now they are againſt me, and would invalidate my
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150258:18"/>Teſtimonie, for my diſcovering the truth concerning the ſaid Earl, and for my diſcharging my Allegiance; which if I had not done, it might have proved of ill conſequence to his Majeſties intereſt: they alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing me Safetie and Bribes if I would not diſcover. And whereas it may be objected the ſmalneſs of my intereſt in the Countrie, it is well known, that not one man in the Countrie had the like intereſt amongſt the ordinarie ſort: and I could have raiſed as many men as one of a great deal more ſubſtance; which was the occaſion of my being drawn into this evil Contrivance, which through Gods providence was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and by my Confeſſion (though I was long kept from it by the Earl's and Mr. <hi>Ely</hi>'s promiſes of reward and preferment) may become of great uſe to the King and Countrie; which time may diſcover, although at preſent the Prieſt excommunicates me, and the voices of evil Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates and their Allies are open againſt me. And I do declare, that my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion was got from me not onely through fear, but out of love I had to that Religion I had formerly profeſſed, which was got ſo near my heart: That bloud which I muſt have been guiltie of, my Conſcience would not ſuffer me to ſhed; nor would I leave that Allegiance which was due to my gracious Soveraign. And I do bleſs God for my Return from that helliſh bloudie Plot, and do pray the Readers favourable Conſtruction of him that is, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a devoted Servant to the publick good of King and Kingdom,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>John Macnemarrah.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="vindication">
               <head>The Vindication of <hi>Edward Ivie</hi> Gent.</head>
               <p>BEing of no long reſidence in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> I ſhall ſpeak but little of my ſelf. My Relations lived in the Counties of <hi>Devon, Wilts,</hi> and <hi>Somerſetſhire</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> being all very reſponſible men; and I lived moſt of my time in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> in a Town-called <hi>Winecauton,</hi> and was in the late Wars a great ſufferer for his Majeſtie, both in Bodie and Eſtate; and ſince ever readie to ſerve his Majeſtie on all occaſions, eſpecially in times of greateſt danger, as in Sir <hi>Joſeph Wagstaffe</hi>'s Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in which I was an Actor, and for which I was forced to abſcond; and never was counted otherwiſe but a perſon whoſe Teſtimonie was fit to be taken, both Publick and Private.</p>
               <p>Neither do I believe but the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> would look upon me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Character, if I had been a Witneſs for him; elſe he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have endeavoured to have had me entrap Mr. <hi>Samſon,</hi> and to have come in againſt him, as in my Examination is expreſſed: Wherefore all that I ſhall ſay, is, That if through my Teſtimonie I have been the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Mr. <hi>Macnemarrah</hi> his confeſſing and declaring the great danger the Engliſh Proteſtants were in, and the preventing of the ſame, through Gods mercie and the vigilancie of our Superiours; all that I deſire is the accepting of the Endeavours of a Loyal Subject and Servant to his Countrie.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Edw. Ivie.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="vindication">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:150258:19"/>
               <head>The Vindication of <hi>Thomas Samſon</hi> Gent.</head>
               <p>SInce it hath been the uſual practice of the Romiſh Partie, in reference to the late Plot, to aſperſe the Witneſſes for his Majeſtie, endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thereby the purging of their own Faults, by taking in queſtion others; thereby to make the world believe their falſe Reports, and to buzz them in the ears that it is for ſiniſter ends theſe things are brought in queſtion, having little elſe but aſſaſſinating the lives and ſcandalizing their names, to clear their Villanies; as appears by thoſe alreadie murdered, and like to be: And it would be an encouragement to future Evidences, if any of the Kings Evidence could but eſcape their Jeſuitical Pen, blondie Hand, or black Mouths.</p>
               <p>Wherefore as ſomething hath been ſpoken in vindication of the other Evidences, ſo I crave the Readers patience to ſpeak ſomething in my own vindication; which I ſhall endeavour to do, to undeceive the world, by declaring theſe three things:
<list>
                     <item>1. The condition of my Perſon and Family.</item>
                     <item>2. The true Grounds moving me to appear in this Caſe.</item>
                     <item>3. In anſwering the Prejudices and Objections whereby the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed have laboured to traduce and defame me.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> As to my Perſon, I was born in <hi>Sherburne</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet,</hi> of an honeſt and credible Family, being in Marriage and otherwiſe related to the chiefeſt Inhabitants in that place; having paſſed all the Offices of the Town where I lived, under Mr. <hi>Lyford,</hi> and Divine well known by his learned Works, then Miniſter of the place; and after his deceaſe, under the labours of others, in a firm adherence to the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for above thirtie years: But after the deceaſe of my Wife, I went into <hi>Ireland</hi> to gather up ſome Debts of my own, and others by whom I was employed. And after my arrival there in <hi>Ireland,</hi> I lived moſt in the Province of <hi>Munſter,</hi> being acquainted with moſt of the Nobilitie and Gentrie of the Counties therein; where a Certificate of my Life and Converſation might, if deſired, have been eaſily procured: for I deſie the world to charge me with any Miſdemeanours which may in the leaſt render me uncapable of being a Witneſs for the King, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſons in any Judicial proceedings; or that can otherwiſe blemiſh my Reputation: Yea, the very Tenants of the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> himſelf, not intereſted or pre-engaged, will teſtifie for me; and three of the Jurie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined before the Council, did on their Oaths ſwear that they never knew or heard any evil Action done by me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> The Motives engaging me to make this Diſcoverie, after a long forbearance of the ſame, when ſummoned up to the Council, was,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The fear of God; which ſhould be the ground of all our Actions and Undertakings: for that will not allow a man to approve Guilt in himſelf, or conceal it in others, eſpecially when the Confequence is ſo por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentous as to threaten Ruine to the King and Countrie; which would have been involved in the common Calamitie, if real, as it ſeemed to appear.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Love to the Proteſtant Religion; which muſt needs be in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, if not quite extirpated, if a forraign Papal power had the upper hand in that Kingdom, the Papiſts having ſo great a part alreadie.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:150258:19"/>
               <p n="3">3. My Dutie and Allegiance to his Majeſtie, <hi>Ireland</hi> having for ſome hundred years been his and his Royal Predeceſſors; ſo that no good Subject could poſſibly hear any thing tending to the rending it out of his Majeſties hands, and being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lled thereunto on Oath, but muſt teſtifie his truth therein, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ld <hi>Tyron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of Iriſh Extraction, had in Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s days ende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>red to betray it unto the Spaniſh, who by Gods Mercie and Engliſh Valour, were ferreted out. Being ſatisfied ſin my Conſcience of Endeavours to betray it to the French now, I looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my ſelf under a deep Engagement no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to conceal it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. I will not deny but that Self-preſervation and Command of Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, had alſo ſome influence upon my Diſcoverie in concurrence with the former Motives. Having diſcovered ſome dangerous Intrigues, I thought it hazardous to conceal them, there being no Acceſſaries in Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but Concealers as well as Actors, coming under the ſame Guilt; and the rather incited thereunto by his Majeſties Proclamation, ſignifying, That if the Diſcoverie were not made by a day appointed, there was no Pardon to the Diſcoverers. Herein I hope, amongſt the intelligent ſort of mankind, I have not laid in any great prejudice againſt my Teſtimonie, becauſe Self-preſervation is a natural Principle which runs through the whole Species of mankind: And yet I confeſs I had ſome ſtruglings in my ſelf, before I could conquer thoſe difficulties which lay in my way; I mean, thoſe prejudices which I foreſaw would be objected againſt me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly.</hi> The Objections and Prejudices I foreſaw, were theſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1. I was comparatively but a mean and inferiour perſon, and therefore unfit to act in ſo high a Concern, and againſt ſo potent a Power, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally having the harſh uſage of Mr. <hi>Bourke</hi> before my eyes. It was a Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as I remember, of Sir <hi>Walter Rawly, That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f a man followed the Truth too cloſe by the heels, it might perhaps knock out his brains.</hi> For an inferiour perſon to accuſe great men, doth many times make the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſuffer, and ſet the Offender free. Truth, it's but ſeldom entertained for its own ſake, that it hath need of piecing advantages to buoy it up againſt the power of great Perſons. This, I confeſs, put ſome ſtop on me for a while, until the former Conſiderations did out-ballance them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There was much danger of Life, Libertie, loſs of Employment, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen by me; which are Clogs and Weights hindring the attempts of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny noble Actions; it being the predictions of moſt perſons, that ſuch would attend thoſe that appeared therein. Conſidering likewiſe the many Slanders and Reproaches that was caſt upon us by the Earls Friends, and to reckon up all the Abuſes and Threatnings againſt me and the reſt of the Witneſſes, ſome of which are hereafter mentioned, would be te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious; if love to Truth had not carried us on, it was impoſſible we ſhould have been ſupported under them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is alleadged as a Diſparagement to me, that I appeared againſt my Lord and Maſter, for ſuch the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> had been, which is counted a thing of no credit for a former Servant to do. To which I ſay, I was the Earl's Steward, for which I had his Commiſſion, and do acknowledge it the dutie of a Steward to be true and faithful to his Maſter, in things wherein the ſafetie of King and Kingdom are not concerned: Yea, and to perſiſt in that frame of reſpect, as long as matters will bear any favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable interpretation, it being the part of a Servant to take all in the beſt ſence. And I my ſelf was ſo far excuſable herein, that at firſt when I heard the Earl ſpeak ſome diſcontented words, I thought them merely indited from his paſſion, of other particular preſſure, without any real or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150258:20"/>ſolid ground; which made me go ſo far in concealing, or rather acting for the Earl, that I could hardly retrieve my Allegiance.</p>
               <p>Yea, his Lordſhip when he was accuſed by <hi>Bourke,</hi> I was very forward to appear for him, as thinking him wrong'd; and accordingly accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him to <hi>Dublin</hi> to that purpoſe: ſo that I was not the firſt Starter of the buſineſs againſt the Earl, but was brought in by the information of Mr. <hi>Bourke;</hi> and I was ſo paſſionately zealous for him, that I could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly retrieve my Allegiance.</p>
               <p>Indeed upon ſerious recollecting of things, and confidering that the faid Earl had a conſtant defiance to the King; and alſo the multitude of Papiſts, and other Iriſh Officers diſbanded in <hi>France,</hi> reſorting to my Lord, and harboured by him, I was convinced that a tranſient diſcontent could not form it ſelf unto ſo great a deſigne, but that it muſt have a fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer root: And thereupon began to obſerve things more narrowly, and then found matter enough to ground more than a Suſpition, and did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there was ſome truth in <hi>Bourk</hi>'s Information. Being alſo further a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened by the Plots in <hi>England</hi> againſt his Majeſty and Government, I had a great conflict in my ſelf what to do. At laſt the nobleſt conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion weighed down all the reſt, and I reſolved to maugre all fears and doubts, and teſtifie the truth; reſolving that it was not an incumbant dutie on a Servant, utterly to loſe his own Reputation to piece up his Maſters.</p>
               <p>Whereupon I made ſeveral days to make ſome diſcoverie at <hi>Kilkenny</hi> to the Lord Lieutenant, but did not then effectually proceed; but then I acquainted Eſquire <hi>Bradley</hi> (which after was charged) one of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Juſtices of the Peace, who told me that he dare not meddle for fear the <hi>Iriſh</hi> would fire his houſe and burn his Family. Whereupon I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took a Journey to <hi>Youghall</hi> to the Earl of <hi>Orrery</hi> for to get his advice and counſel, but found him in a dying condition. In the mean time God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf open'd a door unto me for my Diſcoverie: for upon Mr. <hi>Bourke</hi>'s In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation I was ſent for by the Lord Lieutenant and Council, to declare my knowledge of that matter; which having before diſ-engaged my ſelf from the Earl's ſervice, I was the freer to do. And having before ſeen the great ſwarms of Papiſts flocking to the ſaid Earl's houſe, thirtie or fortie more than our own Family. I alſo conſidering the pretended ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of his Eſtate, for fear of Mr. <hi>Bourke</hi> his charge againſt him, in caſe the Treaſon was found.</p>
               <p>All theſe things conſidered, I leave my ſelf to the Cenſure of all unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted perſons, whether my dutie to my Prince and love to my inperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Religion, ought not to over-ballance the inferiour conſideration of being a Servant to Lord and Maſter, if he had been ſo at that time; which he was not, when thoſe two references do enterfere one with the other.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It's objected againſt me, that I left the Earl and turned head againſt him, becauſe I could not make up my Accompts; and that ſo I covered my diſhoneſty under a pretence of Loyalty.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, That there is no truth in the Allegation, as they that know the Earl's concerns, may eaſily judge: for that I was not in his ſervice above eight months, and having never or ſcarcely above 10 <hi>s.</hi> in my hands, but as the Rent was received, or before it was ordered to be paid away. And if at any time I undertook a Journey of a nights ſtay abroad, I left with the ſaid Earl my Money and Books, for fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing robbed, and the Robberie put on my ſelf; a trick which I was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150258:20"/>of by my Friends, and the Earl's too. The truth of this I leave to the Countrie-Gentlemen, whether they have not heard the Earl ſpeak it to my commendation.</p>
               <p>And of all the Years Rents that came to my hands, was not with other Receipts above 500 <hi>l.</hi> (what Eſtate the Earl had more, I know not) for which I was accountable; out of which was paid 300 <hi>l.</hi> and more in ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Bills, and old Debts, and Rent-charges on the Eſtate: which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, with the charge of Law, Building, Improvements, Journeys to <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> Maintenance of the Houſe, buying almoſt all we uſed: And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times when well freighted with Iriſh Gentlemen and diſbanded Officers out of <hi>France,</hi> it coſt in Extraordinaries above 10 <hi>l.</hi> a week; ſpending more in the Popiſh Faſting-days, being always two or three days in a week, than would maintain a well-govern'd Proteſtant Family the whole week.</p>
               <p>But to give no more ſuch needleſs Excuſes, I paſſed that Account of the firſt half years Rent to <hi>John Power</hi> Eſq; of <hi>Clachmore,</hi> the Earl's Kinſman, and by the Earl his order: and having charged my ſelf with the Receipt of the whole Rental, the Earl was in my debt 30<hi>l.</hi> which I owed at <hi>Waterford.</hi> And to make me take up more there, he gave me a Rental of the next half year; which being ſo ſmall, and ſo great Debts charged on it, that the Earl himſelf could not think on a way how to make proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for that Journey he was then going to <hi>Dublin,</hi> and to pay the old Scores. But I was forced to ſtay behinde and drive the Tenants Cattle; and what Rents could not be had, to take a Bill for on my word in <hi>Waterford,</hi> and ſo have the remainder of the Rents made over to me to diſcharge the ſame.</p>
               <p>At the Earl's return from <hi>Dublin</hi> I was earneſt to diſcharge my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts and Stewardſhip, and in order thereunto got the aforeſaid <hi>John Power</hi> to ſollicit the ſaid Earl to audit my Accompts; who accordingly did, and himſelf made up my Accompt by Acquittances, which the Earl allowed him to paſs, and in the behalf of the Earl to ſet his hand to them. On which all the Arrears due from the Tenants was due to me, having charged my ſelf with the whole Rental and Charge as received; which the ſaid <hi>John Power,</hi> by the Earls order, was ordered to acquaint the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants with: which Arrears I was a fortnight gathering, and diſtraining for at the Earls own door. And what Arrears was due, and I could not then receive, I took Bond for in the Earls own houſe in my own name; which I after ſued for and recovered at the next Aſſizes: which the Earl never found fault with, until (as you may ſee in my Examination) I denied his Gentleman to appear for him the ſaid Earl at the Aſſizes, in Mr. <hi>Bourke</hi>'s abſence; and when I would not appear for him, then he pretended that he was not ſatisfied in his Accounts, and deſired to have them examined again: and then every penny to the very Work-men was alſo examined and proved, and others that were brought to deny what they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and diſcharged under their hands, went away with great ſhame. <hi>John Power</hi> returning to the Earl, ordered me to wait on the Earl in the Field, where he diſcharged me with many Threats. I paſſed the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt ſo often and ſo well, that the ſaid <hi>John Power</hi> ſaid, that he defied the whole world to ſhew a better or honeſter Accompt; on which the Earl was Debtor to me 10<hi>l.</hi> 10<hi>s.</hi> 5<hi>d.</hi> on the Ballance.</p>
               <p>All Gentlemen that know the Earls Concerns, can, if they pleaſe, ſay that the Earl yet never parted with any Steward but gave him the like ſcandalous parting; no, not ſo much as Mr. <hi>John Power</hi> himſelf, who was as to the Earls concerns, in all mens eſteem, a very honeſt man.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:150258:21"/>
               <p>And when I was ſummoned up to Council-board, then he got me arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the way; which Suit the Lord Lieutenant offered to free me from. Yet I anſwered the Suit to avoid the ſcandal, and then the Earl let fall his Suit; and as Counſellor <hi>Porter</hi> ſaid, he believed that the Earl knew not of it; and farther ſaid, that he was ſure he could not certainly ſue me, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as he had ſeen the Accounts, and which were ſo juſt and legal. Judge <hi>Keeling</hi> well obſerving, that if I had been as great a Rogue as <hi>Clanſey,</hi> he was ſure I could not cheat him in his Rents. But to ſatisfie the world more fully, I am ready to paſs it again, if fairly thereto admitted; or to refer the farther ſcanning the ſame to indifferent men, provided one of them is a Proteſtant.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Objection laid in againſt me was, of being bribed by others to throw the Treaſon on the ſaid Earl.</p>
               <p>This Cloud, though black, or blacker than the former, may flie away as ſoon as the other: For the Earl himſelf cannot think ſo, when he knows that Maj. <hi>Butler</hi> was ordered to put this on foot againſt Col. <hi>Villiars,</hi> as ſoon as the Earl heard that Mr. <hi>Bourke</hi> had charged him; concluding that the world would believe it, becauſe of the Law-ſuit that had been betwixt them; which certainly the Colonel had then no need to do, having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Eſtate from the Earl.</p>
               <p>And when examined by the Chief Juſtice on Oath, whether I was a Steward to Col. <hi>Villiars,</hi> I anſwered, That I was not; but if free, I would, foraſmuch as he was a good Proteſtant, and a Loyal Subject. And when the Queſtion was put to the Colonel, whether he had employed me, he anſwered, That he had heard by the Country that I was an honeſt man; and if free from the Kings concerns in this Examination, he would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy me. And one thing I obſerved of the ſaid Colonel was, that when he had a Witneſs examined on a Commiſſion about a weighty affair, he then told the perſon, encouraging him to ſpeak truth, that he had rather loſe his Eſtate, than to keep it by a falſe Oath.</p>
               <p>And I do hereby declare, in the preſence of God, that I never had one Penny bribe from him or others in my life.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Hopes of Reward in the laſt place charged as a Motive inducing me to this Undertaking.</p>
               <p>To which I ſay, That my Carriage in both Kingdoms will be my Compurgators from this Charge. I have been always more a Friend to others than to my ſelf, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtraightned my ſelf to do others good. Beſides, the Accuſation contradicts it ſelf; to loſe a certain Employ for uncertain Hopes, is not the part of a prudent man. I did eaſily foreſee the Troubles, by Threats and Menaces to others, and did not expect leſs to fall on me; and which at length came to paſs, the Knife being taken out of the hand of one going to ſtab me: and for me to diſpoſſeſs my ſelf of a quiet and peaceable Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Livelihood, and thereby, as it were, to court my own Trouble and Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, is not to be imagined I ſhould have done, unleſs higher Motives had engaged me. I was but an ill Carver for my ſelf, the way I took, if my aim was only at Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. All mens judgments (which are but fallible) will be at laſt ſurveyed and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at a higher Tribunal; and if then it appear that the firſt recited Motives put me up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Diſcovery, and do ſtill ſupport me againſt all Diſcouragements under it, I ſhall be then ſufficiently acquitted before God (as I am at preſent in my own Conſcience) whatſoever Slanders, Obloquies, and Reproaches, the Envy of Adverſaries doth caſt in my way, to aſperſe, black, and defame me.</p>
               <p>Theſe things I have offered to the view of the World, in reſpect of my Allegiance, knowing it my duty, that if I ſaw but a Cloud as big as my hand, I ought to diſcover it to my Maſter the King; and alſo in love to my ſelf to ſecure me againſt ſuch Scandals, which otherwiſe might be a hindrance to Truth.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>THO. SAMSON.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
